music
music
applause
applause
We invite you to the Institute of Molecular Biology of our hospital tonight
我們今天晚上請到本院分子生物研究所
The special evaluation researcher of the inspection team came to tell us
檢診領特評研究員來跟我們講
Then we also have an online live broadcast
那我們同時還有線上直播
Teacher Na Jian graduated from the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University.
那檢老師是台大化學系畢業
Then went to the State University of New York to study for a Ph.D.
然後到美國紐約州大學念的博士
when he was a doctor
那他在博士時候
developed a very important experimental method
就發展了一個非常重要的實驗方法
The two-hybrid approach we call Filial Mother Army
我們叫做孝母軍的雙雜交方法
This is used to test the binding between protein and protein
這個是用來測試蛋白質跟蛋白質之間的結合
Because this method was later widely used
因為這一個方法後來被非常廣泛的應用
It is a very important research tool in biology
在生物學界是非常重要的一個研究的工具
His teacher was elected a member of the American Academy of Sciences for this
他的老師因為這個獲選美國的科學院院士
This is what he did when he was a doctor
這是他博士時候做的
After his postdoctorate, he went to the Faculty of the University of California
博士後他就到了加州大學的究竟學院
Returned to the Institute of Molecular Biology of our school in 1996
在1996年回到本院的分子生物研究所
right in my lab we're next door
就在我的實驗室 我們是隔壁
Teacher Jian’s research in recent years has not only done
檢老師的研究近年來除了做
research institutes also research institutes
研究的研究所 也有研究的研究
Returned to the Institute of Molecular Biology of our school in 1996
在1996年回到本院的分子生物研究所
right in my lab we're next door
就在我的實驗室 我們是隔壁
Check teacher's research in recent years
檢老師的研究近年來
In recent years, in addition to doing basic nervous system development
近年來除了做基礎的神經系統的發育之外
also started to work on neurodegenerative diseases
也開始做到神經退化疾病的
some related research
一些的相關的研究
it has won many awards
它得了非常多的獎
Including our Academy's Young Scholar Book Award
包括本院的年輕學者著作獎
Excellence Award from the Ministry of Science and Technology
科技部的傑出獎
Academic Awards of the Ministry of Education Hou Jindui Research Award
教育部的學術獎 侯金堆研究獎
Taiwan's Science and Technology Award
然後台化的科技獎
He also does a lot of service work
他也做很多的服務性的工作
Including serving as the chairman of this basic neurological society in Taiwan
包括擔任台灣的這個基礎神經學會的理事長
Then he will tell us a very interesting topic today
那他今天要跟我們講一個很有趣的題目
walking with neurologists
叫做與神經員同行
Then he's going to talk about fate, fairness and competition.
那他要談命運 公平和競爭
From the aspects of learning, degeneration and medical treatment of the nervous system
那從這個神經系統的學習 退化和醫療這些方面來講
Then we welcome Teacher Shoulder
那我們歡迎肩老師
Okay, thank you grandson Mi for the introduction.
好 謝謝那個孫子咪的介紹
Then I came back to Taiwan for about 22 years
那我回來台灣大約22年
That's very trustworthy and Sun Zimi is the laboratory next door
那很有信跟孫子咪是隔壁實驗室
It's always been the lab next door
一直都是隔壁實驗室
So besides his family, the person he sees the most should be me
所以他除了他家人以外看到最多人應該是我
I am very happy that I can give a speech here today
那很高興就是說今天能夠在這邊給一個演講
Then this is a challenge for us
那這個對我們來講是一個挑戰
Because it is a popular science speech
因為是一個科普的演講
Then I'll try to put my research over the years
那我會試著把我這多年來的研究
compare with what i think
用我覺得比較
My normal language to speak to you
我一般的語言來跟大家講
but if it's too simple
但是如果太簡單的話
Please forgive me too
也請大家見諒
Help me stop if it's too hard
如果太難的話也可以幫我停下
feel free to ask no problem
隨時都可以問這樣沒有問題
What I tell you today is
我今天跟大家講的是
In fact, neurons
事實上是講神經元的
neurons
就是神經細胞神經元
This topic was first ordered by my students
這個題目是我先是學生幫我訂的
Because they said that there was a Korean movie called
因為他們說最近有一部韓國的電影叫
"Rain God" is very popular
《雨神通行》非常流行
Me and some Korean drama students come to listen to this
我跟韓國戲一些學生來聽這樣子
so i ordered one
所以我就訂了一個
Title of "Rain Neuron Pass"
《雨神經元通行》的題目
In fact we want to say
事實上我們是想說
look at nerve cells or neurons
看神經細胞或者神經元
Its whole development and whole heredity
它整個發育還有整個遺傳
how to decide its itinerary
來怎麼決定它的行程的過程
as if i'm next to you
好像是我在旁邊
look at a nerve cell
看著一個神經細胞
From birth to differentiation to aging
從出生到分化到老化
process to death
到死亡的過程
what the hell is a change
到底是什麼一個變化
between cells
到底有細胞跟細胞之間
And what is the relationship between cells and genes?
還有細胞跟基因之間有什麼樣的
Interactions or what a regulation looks like
交互作用或一個調控的樣子
Then I returned to Taiwan 22 years ago
那我22年前回到台灣
Then go to the branch office
然後就到分生所
Then the first thing is to get married and have children
然後第一件事情就是結婚生小孩
And here are my two kids
然後這是我兩個小孩
That photo from 20 years ago
那個20年前的照片
Then the model organisms in our laboratory
那我們實驗室的模式生物
is made with fruit flies
是用果蠅在做
Every model organism looking at the organisms of Drosophila
每個模式生物在看果蠅的生物
Of course, watch your child grow up
那當然看自己小孩長大
This is actually a model organism
這其實也是一個模式生物
is a model organism for a person
是一個人的模式生物
then i feel very curious
那我覺得很好奇
You will find that these two children
你會發現說這兩個小孩
why does it look so similar
為什麼長得這麼像
Of course, this is very simple.
那當然這個很簡單就是說
Both parents have the same genes
父母親的基因都是一樣的
The other point is that
那另外一點就是說
Except very...
除了很...
so we know that
所以我們知道說
the process by which genes contribute to the formation of an organism
基因對一個生物體的形成過程
In fact, it has a big, big impact like this
其實是有很大很大的影響這樣子
But the two are not exactly the same, right?
但是兩個也不是完全一樣對不對
Because their genes can't be exactly the same
因為他們兩個的基因不可能完全一樣
There is a part of father and part of mother.
有一部分爸爸一份媽媽的這樣子
So this is what caused me to be interested in this gene
所以說這個是引起我對這個基因
This one with the research topic of development...
有發育這個研究主題的這個...
At the same time, we also use nerve cells
那同時我們也是用神經細胞
It is neurons that are the subject of this study
就是神經元來做這個研究的題材
so before starting
所以在開始之前
I'll tell you first
我先跟大家
easy
簡單的喔
I think many people may also know
我想可能很多人也清楚
But still take a little time
不過還是花一點點時間喔
with everyone
跟大家
ditch this
溝疏一下這個
tell everyone about this
跟大家講一下這個
The definition of a few simple nouns of neurons
神經元的幾個簡單的名詞上的定義喔
Then the definition of this noun you heard
那這個名詞定義你聽了
You may be very clear to many people
你可能很多人很清楚喔
but if you haven't heard
但如果沒有聽過的話
you can follow me
你就可以跟著我一起
Let's memorize these words for a while
來把這些字喔稍微記一下
it's easier to wait
那等一下比較容易
You can memorize the process as I told you.
跟著我講的這個過程可以記下來喔
Then the nerve cells seen here
那這裡看到的幾個神經細胞
everyone can see
大家可以看得到
Oh, the nerve cells
那神經細胞喔
In fact, a nerve cell
其實一個神經細胞
a cell
一個細胞喔
its own function
本身的功能喔
It's not really obvious
其實不太明顯
the nerve cells
那神經細胞就要
one after the other
一顆接著一顆連在一起
one after another
一顆連著一顆連著一顆
Then such a nerve will form a
那這樣神經要形成一個
So-called
所謂的
to connect together
要連接在一起
forming one
形成一個
network time
網絡的時候
it only has one
它才有一個
a function is here
一個功能在喔
So the nerve cells
那所以神經細胞這些
to be connected together
要連在一起
basically i
基本上我
We can divide it into three parts from its type
我們就可以從它的型態上把它分三部分
You can see that this neuron
大家可以看到說這個神經元
The most important thing is a neural ontology
最重要就是一個神經的本體
an ontology
一個本體
just like its body itself
就是它的身體的本身這樣子
This provides the entire nerve cell with very high
這提供整個神經細胞非常多的
may be some protein
可能是一些蛋白質
RNA or some kind of nutrient
RNA或是一些什麼樣的養分
or something
或怎麼樣的
so that the nerve can have a normal function like this
讓神經可以有一個正常的功能這樣子
So there is a cell's body
所以有一個細胞的本體
In addition, there is a long plant called axon, which is very long
另外有一個長廠的非常長的一個叫軸突的
The nerve cell itself has a very long one
神經細胞本身有一個非常長的一個
we can see say
我們可以看到說
Almost every nerve cell has an axon like this
每一個神經細胞幾乎都有一個軸突這樣子
The axon is actually what everyone remembers that the axon is a
軸突其實就是大家記得軸突就是一個
send a signal in one direction
送訊號出去的一個方向
That is to say, the nerve cell body
就是說這神經細胞本體
it sends the signal out
它把訊號送出去
sent out from the axon like this
從軸突送出去這樣子
sent to the next nerve cell
送到下一個神經細胞
What part does the nerve cell receive
神經細胞接收的部分是哪一部分
it's called speed
它就叫速突
just stand out
就是突出來的
it's the other end
它另外一頭
mostly the other end
大部分就是另外一頭
It has some quite forked
它有一些蠻多分叉的
There are quite a lot of forks. This is called Sutu.
蠻多分叉的 这个叫宿兔
Then this old rabbit is receiving the signal
那这个宿兔是在接受讯号
So everyone remembers that there is an ontology
所以大家记得有一个本体
There's an axis rabbit, there's an old rabbit like this
那有一个軸兔 那有一个宿兔这样子
Then the neuron can
然后神经细胞就可以
one after another
一个跟一个接在一起
So we see here that
所以我们这里看到说
Here are two nerve cells
这里有两颗神经细胞
Then this is its body, the axis rabbit
那这个是它的本体 这个軸兔
If the axis rabbit, the tail will be forked
那軸兔的话尾巴会分叉
That's the rabbit with another cell
那跟另外细胞的宿兔
it can be connected together
它就可以连接在一起
form a ratio of possibly several connections
形成可能好几个连接的比
The place where this connection is called Tutu
那这个连接的地方叫图兔
Because there is a place where the axis rabbit and the old rabbit come into contact
因为有軸兔跟宿兔接触的地方
It's called Tutu
它叫图兔
That's where the two pictures came out
就是两个图出来的地方
The place of contact is called Tutu
接触的地方叫图兔
that's where they communicate
那这就是他们沟通交流的地方
This axis rabbit handles the signal
这个軸兔把讯号
a telegram
一个电讯号送过来
And then to this point of contact
然后到了这个接触的地方
some chemical molecules
就有一些化学分子
and then to the next neuron
然后给下一颗神经细胞
Receive the signal and pass it on
接到讯号就再传下去
So we can say
所以我们就可以说
In our brain, there are actually many, many such nerve cells connected with nerve cells
在我們大腦裡面其實有非常非常多的這種神經細胞跟神經細胞連結
Then pass the signal through to make a thing
然後把訊號穿過去可以做一個東西
So we have a lot of new networks in our brains like this
所以我們大腦裡面有非常多新的網絡這樣子
You can say that it is a very complex network interaction effect
大家可以想說是一個非常複雜的網絡交互的作用
we can ask
我們就可以問說
How many neurons are there in our brain
我們大腦裡面到底有多少神經元
Then how much prominence
然後有多少的突出
how many complex networks
有多少的多複雜的網絡
In fact, people often compare the planets in this universe with the nerve cells in the brain
其實常常有人拿這個宇宙的星球跟大腦裡面神經細胞的比較
Who is more like this
到底誰比較多這樣子
This is of course I copied it from that Euclopedia
這個是我當然是從那個Euclopedia上抄下來
That is to say, the star shape of the Milky Way is about 10 to the 11th power
就是說銀河系的星型大概是10的11次方格
The star shape of the universe is about 10 to the 23rd power
宇宙的星型大概是10的23次方格
There are about 1011 grids of neurons in the brain
大腦裡面神經元大概有10的11次方格
very very many
非常非常多
Each person's brain is about 10 to the 11th power
每一個人的大腦裡面大概是10的11次方格
Then you are similar to the star shape of our Milky Way in the universe
那你就跟宇宙的我們銀河系的星型比起來是差不多的
Neural gardens can form about a thousand
神經園大概可以形成一千個
contact with another thousand neurons
跟另外一千個神經細胞接觸
It's like a thousand synapses
就是一千個突觸這樣子
So there are about 14 synapses
所以大概就有14次方的突觸
So it looks like it is much less than the stars in the universe
所以看起來跟宇宙的星星比起來是少多
The cells of this neural garden are almost as careful as tremella
這個神經園的細胞差不多跟銀耳細心差不多
But then I thought
不過後來想到說
Hey, we're not alone
欸 我們也不是一個人
not alone in this world
在這個世界上不是一個人
there are so many people in our world
我們這個世界上有這麼多人
Then every person often we have some collective behaviors
那每一個人常常我們有一些集合的一些行為
Bubble our cultural creation
泡泡我們的文化上的創造啦
scientific research
科學上的研究啦
So if we add up the synapses of humans all over the world
那如果我們把全世界人類的突觸加在一起的話
only the 24th square
就只有24次方格
So this is actually a very large number.
所以這個其實是非常大的一個數字
so for us to say
所以對我們來講說
Hey, we want to study the structure of this neural garden
欸 我們想要研究這個神經園的結構
its birth its formation
它的出生 它的形成
And what's the function of its whole connection together?
那還有它的整個連結在一起什麼功能
that's a very interesting subject
那這是一個非常有趣的課題
Not only are there many nerve cells
那神經細胞不只多
In addition to so many nerve cells in our brain
我們大腦裡面出了這麼多的神經細胞之外
We also have a lot of complex different
我們還有很多複雜的不同的
We have types of nerve cells
我們有種類的神經細胞
Then let's show you this again
那大家再給大家看一下這個
there are many
這裡面就有非常多
show a very wide variety of nerve cells
秀出非常多種類的神經細胞
inside our brain
在我們大腦裡面
Then you can see that there is a very simple
那大家可以看到說有非常簡單的
like this one
像這一種
We call it granule cells like this
我們把它叫顆粒細胞這樣子
This accounts for more than 50% of the brain
這在大腦裡面大概占了百分之五十以上的
Then of course we have very complex
那當然我們有很複雜的
like this one in the cerebellum
像這個在小腦裡面的一個
Putin's One Cell
普京式的一個細胞
you can see say
你可以看到說
its quick burst
它的速突
Sutu The Sutu we just talked about is the signal place
速突我們剛剛講的速突就是訊號的地方
In fact, the bifurcation is very powerful.
其實分岔的非常厲害
You can see that it keeps forking
你可以看到說它一直在分岔
It really looks like a tree
長得真的是像一棵樹這樣子
and the motor neurons on our spine
那還有我們脊椎上面的運動神經元
There are so many motor nerve cells in our spine
我們的脊椎上面非常多的運動神經細胞
Then you can see that it is also
那你可以看到說它也是
A nerve cell has many branches
一個神經細胞都有非常多的分岔
Then finally inside our cerebral cortex
那最後我們的大腦皮層裡面
There are a lot of this so-called
有非常多這個所謂的
vertebral neurons
椎體神經元
Then this is the same as our human beings later
那這個跟我們這個人類後來
A neuron involved in this cognitive aspect
這個認知方面有關的一種神經元
There are many such
也是非常多這樣子
So we can see that in fact we
所以我們可以看到說其實我們
In addition to a lot of
大腦裡面除了非常多的
outside of nerve cells
神經細胞之外
We also have many different types of Shenyin cells
我們還有非常多種類不同的神音細胞
Well, this is actually a big problem for us.
那這個其實對我們來講是一個很大的問題
That is to say, in addition to the fact that our brains need to grow a lot of divine sound cells
就是說除了我們大腦要長出非常多神音細胞之外
How do we control and grow different Shenyin cells?
我們去怎麼去控制去長出不同的神音細胞的樣子出來
You can do different functions like this
可以做不同的功能這樣子
throughout our development
我們在整個過程中 整個發育過程中
Then how does this cause different Shenyin cells to come out?
那這到底是怎麼樣造成不同的神音細胞出來
allows us to perform different jobs like this
可以讓我們執行不同的工作這樣子
Well, this is actually very complicated because the brain is too complicated
那這個其實是很複雜 因為大腦太複雜
Then too many different kinds of Shenyin cells
然後太多不同種類的神音細胞
So my subjects are actually fruit flies.
所以我的研究體才其實是果蠅
Then we have to simplify the problem to say
那我們就必須把這問題簡化 簡化成說
Then I will ask a Shenyin cell, a certain Shenyin cell
那我去問一顆神音細胞 某一個神音細胞
How on earth did it grow and grow like this?
它到底是怎麼樣長出來 長出這個樣子
Then we use a steel wool from a fruit fly
那我們就是用果蠅身上的一根鋼毛
It's called steel wool, which means you can see the fruit flies.
這個名字叫鋼毛 就是說大家可以看到果蠅
If you have seen fruit flies
如果大家有看到果蠅的話
There are a lot of these thin ones on its back
它背部上有非常多一根一根這種細細的
Then the steel wool is actually a sensory organ of the nerves.
那這個鋼毛其實是一個神經的感覺器官
under it there is a hair growing on the outside
它底下 它外面長了一根毛之外
it has a nerve cell underneath it
它底下有一個神經細胞
So when you touch this it's outside this hair
所以當你碰這個 它外在這個毛的時候
The nerve cells underneath it will have a feeling
它底下神經細胞會有一個感覺
This signal is then sent to the state-run central nervous system
然後會把這個訊號傳到國營的中樞神經區
That's why the state-owned company knows that someone touches it like this
所以國營知道有人才碰它這樣子
In fact, there are a lot of people in the state camp
那事實上國營身上長得非常多
you can see a lot of roots
你可以看到非常多根
And it's very neatly arranged
而且排列得非常整齊
Then there are some gaps in the middle like this
然後中間有一些縫隙這樣子
This is a state run one
這個是一個國營的一個
Then when I was doing postdoctoral research at the time
那我那時候做博後在博士後研究的時候
while in san francisco
在舊金山的時候
In fact, the research is such a simple question that
其實研究就是這麼簡單的一個問題就是說
How did this steel wool come about?
那這個一根鋼毛到底是怎麼出生的
In fact, after years of research, a researcher found that
那其實一個做了多年研究後發現說
In fact, the simple thing is that fate is destiny
其實滿簡單的就是命運就是天注定
That is to say, these steel wool
就是說這些鋼毛
What kind of nerve organelles grow under it
它的底下長成什麼樣的神經細胞器
It was doomed when it was born
上天它一出生的時候就注定了
Then we can see that
那我們可以看到說
One advantage of using Guina for research is that
用鬼那做研究一個好處就是
We can mutate a gene
我們可以把一個基因給突變掉
So we call a gene a proneural gene
所以我們把一個基因叫做原神經基因
It is a gene related to the formation of nerve cells
它就跟神經細胞要形成有關的一個基因
When it can be removed, you saw that it was on the back of the fruit camp
可以去掉的時候你看到說在果營的背部
It was supposed to grow a lot of steel wool
本來要長非常多跟鋼毛的
Actually gone
其實都不見了
It's just a few skin cells left like this
它只剩下一些表皮細胞這樣子
just a skin cell
一個表皮細胞而已
So let's talk about gene expression
所以我們就說說有基因的表達
it can form this steel wool
它就可以形成這個鋼毛
Then it can grow the nerve cells of its sensory organs
然後就可以長出它這種感覺器官的神經細胞
Then you can let it feel these external stimuli
然後可以讓它去感覺這些外在的刺激
Then there are some responses like this
然後有一些反應這樣子
So this proneural gene
所以這個原神經基因
Actually when I come back
其實就是我回來的時候
It is also the beginning of research on this subject
也是開始研究這方面的題材
That is, how do proneural genes work?
就是說原神經基因到底怎麼作用
Well, of course there is not only one kind of fruit camp.
那其實果營當然不是只有一種
sensory nerve cells
感覺器官的神經細胞
Our fruit camp is relatively simple
我們果營比較簡單
So we can in its peripheral nervous system
所以我們可以在它周邊神經系統裡面
see that there are three different types of nerve cells
看到有三種不同的神經細胞
a type of nerve cell called the extrinsic
一種是叫做外在的神經細胞
organ , we just saw that steel hair
器官,我們剛看到那根鋼毛
it can feel the touch
它可以感覺到碰觸的感覺
Under the table, we just can't see under the table
在提表底下,我們剛看不到提表底下
In fact there is another sense organ
事實上有另外一種感覺器官
It's actually feeling the contraction of the muscles
它事實上是可以感覺到肌肉的收縮
or can make it feel balanced
或可以讓它感覺到平衡
it looks very different
它長相非常不一樣
You can see it looks very different than this one
你可以看到它長相非常不一樣跟這個非常不一樣
Another type of neuron called a multivelocity synapse
另外還有一種叫做多速突的神經元
It's very long and fast
它長非常多跟著速突
it also has its function
它也有它的功能
they look very different
它們的長相非常不一樣
They also function very differently
它們的功能也非常不一樣
But how different are they?
可是它們到底有多大的差異
The teacher is when they decide to say
老師在於它們什麼時候才決定說
are they different
它們要不一樣
The question we're asking is that
我們要問的問題就是說
How did this nerve cell become different?
這神經細胞怎麼變得不一樣
that's when it decided it was different
那是什麼時候決定它的不一樣
This is consistent with our research findings
這跟我們研究發現說
very imaginative very different
非常的想像非常的不一樣
It turns out that very, very early in embryonic development, very early
原來很早很早在胚胎發育非常早的時候
At the beginning, it was an epidermal cell formed from outside
一開始還是外配成的一個表皮細胞的時候
He already decided his fate
他就已經決定他的命運了
In other words, the proneural gene we just talked about
也就是說我們剛剛講的原神經基因這個東西
He may have been out very early when he was paired to express a proneural gene
他可能很早在外配成表達一種原神經基因的時候
He decided to become this sensory organ
他就決定他變成這一個感覺器官了
But if another proneural gene is expressed
但如果表達另外一種原神經基因
when it's called etonal
這裡叫etonal的時候
He might have influenced him to change into another form.
他可能就影響他變成另外一種形態
the last amus
最後一個amus
He may also mean that when he expresses
他也可能就是說他一表達的時候
He formed this kind of nerve cells
外配成的他就形成這一種神經細胞
So it echoes what I just said at the beginning
所以就是呼應我剛剛一開始講的說
Although his nerve cells look very different
雖然他這些神經細胞長相非常不一樣
very different functions
功能非常不一樣
But he seems to be at the beginning of his birth
可是他似乎在他一開始出生的時候
His expression of nerve genes has already determined that he becomes a nerve cell
他表達神經基因就已經決定他變成神經細胞了
Then this is a lot like destiny
那這個就是很像是命運天注定
It was doomed early in the morning
那一早就注定好了
He will be able to escape the arrangement of fate
他才會很能逃脫命運的安排
cell fate decisions
細胞命運的決定
Well, this state-run research is actually in this area
那這國營研究其實在這方面
great contribution
貢獻蠻大的
Because these protothec
因為這些原神菌基因
not only in the state
不只在國營有
In fact, his evolution has a very high degree of reservation
其實他的演化上有非常高度的保留
So a lot of it is found in mice
所以在老鼠身上也找到非常多的
Protothecium gene
原神菌基因
Then we know rats are more complicated than state run
那我們知道老鼠比國營複雜多了
He has all sorts of peripheral germ cells
他有各式各樣的周邊的神菌細胞
Then they express different protothecium genes
那他們表達不同的原神菌基因
in different places
在不同的地方
that can decide him
那也可以決定他
Where will you be in the future
未來以後要在什麼地方
Grow this different germ cells out
長出這樣不同的神菌細胞出來
So this looks like a
所以這個看起來就是一個
very simple law
非常簡單的一個定律
that is, gene expression
就是說基因的表達
and very early expression
而且非常早期的表達
can determine the germ cell
就可以決定神菌細胞的
The fate of this future is like this
這個未來的命運這樣子
this is a
這個是一個
pretty simple example
蠻簡單的例子
That
那
But
可是
seems to be a gene expression
好像是一個基因表達
It seems that the decision can be made immediately
好像就馬上可以決定
He's going to turn into a germ cell
他要變成一個神菌細胞
But it's actually that simple
可是事實上是這麼簡單
That in the study found that
那在研究發現說
It's not that simple
其實也不是那麼簡單
Discovered that you are going to become a germ cell
發現說你要變成神菌細胞
You go through a so-called competitive process
你要經過一個所謂的競爭的過程
That's what I said in it
那這個就是我在裡面有講到說
There is also a process of competition between cells
細胞跟細胞之間也有競爭的過程
Then we know that in some epidermis
那我們知道說在一些表皮的
So the surface layer of cells
所以表面那一層細胞
For example, here are 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
譬如說這裡有1 2 3 4 5 6 7
7 cells
7個細胞
Then there is only one of these 7 cells
那這7個細胞只有一顆
7 will only choose one
7個只會選出一顆
to become a nerve cell
要變成一個神經細胞
Come on, that sounds full
好來 那這個聽起來滿
highly competitive
競爭滿激烈的
It's better than the election we just ended
這比我們選舉剛剛結束的選舉
more intense feeling
還要激烈的感覺
7 only one
7個只有一個
Then who and how to choose
那到底要選誰怎麼選
how to compete
怎麼競爭
Then we often want to say that competition has two strategies
那我們常常想說競爭有兩個策略
you would think right
你會想到對不對
how is one
一個是怎麼樣
self-improvement, right?
自我提升對不對
I make myself better
我把我自己變得好一點
I beat others, right?
我比贏過別人對不對
Others got 99 points, I got 100 points
別人考99分 我考100分
i beat him
我就贏過他了
What's another strategy for the competition?
那競爭還有一個什麼策略
Yes, like an election
對 就跟選舉一樣
Initiation marks, right?
發起痕對不對
make others worse
讓別人差一點
Then this competition is actually more practical than a bad strategy
那這個競爭其實用的就是比一個不好的策略
We call it the test of will
我們把它叫做 把它叫測意志
test will
測意志
That is to say
也就是說
If one of the cells wants to become that nerve cell
其中有一個細胞如果要變成那個神經細胞的時候
it sends out a signal
它會發出一個訊號出來
go to the cells next to the consciousness say
去意識旁邊的細胞說
Don't be like me, don't be like a nerve cell
你不要跟我變成一樣 不要變成神經細胞這樣子
ok like this i mean
好 這樣子我的意思
It's just that I'm a volition, you don't want
就是我是一個意志性的 你們不要
don't be like me
你們不要跟我一樣
OK, there is a premise here, that is
OK 那這裡有一個前提就是說
In fact, each of these cells has the potential to become
其實這每個細胞都有可能可以變成
The ability of nerve cells
神經細胞的這個能力
i have the potential
我都有這個潛力
can become nerve cells
可以變成神經細胞
But because of competition
可是因為競爭的結果
Only one can become a nerve cell
只有一顆可以變成神經細胞
Then the rest will retreat back into an epidermal cell
那其他就退回去變成一個表皮細胞而已
OK
OK
How to do this experiment
那這實驗怎麼做
Let's say this is the final conclusion
我們說 這個講起來這個是最後的結論
How about this experiment
那這個實驗上怎麼做
Well, there is actually a very simple experiment that
那其實有一個很簡單的實驗就是
Someone went to observe the embryo and said
有人就去觀察這個胚胎說
Here's a group of cells, and one of them
這裡有一群細胞,然後其中有一顆
seems to start turning into something like a nerve cell
好像要開始變成一個類似像神經細胞
start to change
開始有點變化
I'll take a laser then
那我就拿一個雷射
Strong laser kills this one
強的雷射把這一顆殺死
what happened then?
那發生什麼事?
If this one is going to become a nerve cell and be killed
如果這一顆要變成神經細胞被殺死
What will happen to the other six?
其他六顆會發生什麼事?
Clam?
蛤?
replace, who replaces?
取代,誰取代?
re-compete
重新競爭
you might just say
你就可能就是說
we put that
我們把那個
It seems that the person who is going to be elected will be grinded and killed.
好像要當選那個人給磨殺掉以後
There are six other people to compete, right?
就有其他六個人再去競爭,對不對?
How many people will become nerve cells?
那會有幾個人變成神經細胞?
still one
還是一個
So why is he still one?
那為什麼他還是一個?
six in six
六個裡面,還是六個
the answer is one
答案是一個
It's simple to say
很簡單就是說
Because these six, these seven cells
因為這六,這七個細胞
His ability, has the potential to become a nerve cell
他的能力,有潛力變成神經細胞
He also has the potential to suppress others
他也有潛力去抑制別人
So when we kill this
所以當我們把這個殺了以後
One of the others becomes a nerve cell
其他有一顆就變成神經細胞
He also wants to restrain others
他同時要去抑制別人
I was in class at that time
那這個當年我在上課
when telling jokes
常常講說笑話的時候
I often think of the former Yiqingzhuang case in Taiwan
常常就想到以前台灣的一清莊案
We often arrest gangsters, don't we?
我們常常把黑道大哥給抓起來對不對
It turns out that strategy doesn't work
後來發現那個策略是不行的
Because how about you arrest big brother
因為你把大哥抓起來怎麼樣
Brothers will compete, right?
小弟們就會競爭對不對
Then someone became a big brother
那又有人變成大哥
So this is very troublesome
所以這個是很麻煩的事
And what must the elder brother do?
而且大哥一定要怎麼樣
Because he wants to help other boys, right?
因為他要自助其他的小弟對不對
So here's an experiment that's actually quite interesting
所以這裡一個實驗其實很有意思
That is to say, he has a will
就是說他有個側意志
Cells compete by suppressing others
細胞的競爭其實是靠著去抑制別人
Then this example is a very interesting example
那這個例子是很有趣的例子
Then we see that lateral will
那我們看到說側意志
is this a fair competition
這個是一個很公平的競爭嗎
In fact, our scientists found in the research that
那其實我們的科學家研究裡面發現說
When this side will will produce a
這個側意志的時候會產生一顆
on the surface of this cell through two proteins
透過兩個蛋白質在這個細胞的表面
exchange of
的交換
It sends the signal that you can't be like a neuron
它把訊號傳過去說你不能變成神經細胞這樣子
So there is a saying that proves that this is a gene related to side shifting characters
所以有一種證明這個是跟側移字有關的基因的話
That is to say, you mutate this protein
就是說你把這個蛋白質給突變掉
Let it mutate, make it impossible to pass the signal
讓它突變掉 讓它訊號傳不過去
At this time, it is different from the experimental results just now.
這時候就跟剛剛的實驗結果不一樣
how is it
這時候是怎麼樣
Because I said each one has the potential to become a nerve cell
因為我說每一顆都有潛力要變成神經細胞
So after you cancel the side shifting word
所以你把這個側移字取消掉以後
They have no communication, no competition
他們就沒有溝通 就沒有競爭了
So each of them has become a nerve cell.
所以每一顆都變成什麼 神經細胞了
that's cool
這樣才好意思
So this is a process of shifting characters sideways
所以說這是有一個側移字的過程
Everyone has to compete with each other and you can suppress others
大家有互相競爭 然後你可以抑制別人
Then I now use the genetic method to remove the suppression mechanism
然後我這個現在是用基因的方式把這個抑制的機制給取掉以後
Everyone becomes this nerve cell
大家就變成這個神經細胞
Is there any evidence for this?
那這個有沒有證據
Then I will show you a picture and everyone will know
那我給大家看一個圖片大家就知道
see this one
看到這一個
When we said this was normal
本來我們說這個正常的時候
this one gang
這一根剛某
Next to it are actually epidermal cells
它旁邊其實都是表皮細胞
very many epidermal cells
非常多的表皮細胞
Then you saw that I removed the mechanism of this one
那你看到說我把這隻的機制給去掉
Wow, this is one weight and one weight this
哇 漲成這個一重一重的這個
Steel wool, there are divine sound cells underneath
鋼毛 那底下都有神音細胞
Shenyin cells
一大堆的神音細胞
So this means that we put this mechanism
所以這個就是說我們把這隻的機制
to remove later
給去掉以後
then this this this
然後這個這個這個
Everyone will become Shenyin cells
大家就變成神音細胞
This is how everyone chooses
大家就盪選了這樣子
not bad
還不錯
That
那
that
那個
Then here's another interesting question.
那再來就一個蠻有趣的問題
this
這個
I often say this example in class
我在上課也是常講這個例子
That is to say, once the cell has a cell
就是說那細胞一旦有一顆細胞
I just talked about this cell
就剛剛講這一顆細胞
it is in
它是在
During the competition just now
剛剛那個競爭的過程中
has been selected
已經被選出來了
So in the future you will become like a Shenyin cell
所以以後你要變成神音細胞這樣子
Then does it really become a Shenyin cell?
那它真的變成神音細胞嗎
we later found out that
我們後來發現說
Hey, this process is actually quite laborious.
欸 這個其實過程是蠻辛苦的
it doesn't mean i'm in this
它不是說我在這個
Among seven or eight people, I chose
七八個人中間我選擇了
I will become a divine sound cell
我就變成神音細胞
In fact, there is still a process in the middle
其實中間還有一個過程
This is really going to become a Shenyin cell.
這個真的要變成神音細胞真的是
It's a very hard process, this is a hard process with thousands of mountains and rivers
蠻辛苦的過程,這個是一個千山萬水的辛苦的過程
What about this cell, it divides
這個細胞呢,它會分裂
become two cells, and those two cells are dividing to become two cells
變成兩個細胞,那兩個細胞在分裂變成兩個細胞
This is dividing into two cells like this
這在分裂變成兩個細胞這樣子
In fact, these four cells will form the structure of the anal hair we just talked about.
那其實這種四顆細胞這樣子,會構成剛剛我們講的那個肛毛的結構
So the anal hair itself is composed of four cells
所以這個肛毛本身有四顆細胞所構成
Then it's actually a cell that just competed for the battalion after it splits
那它事實上是一個剛剛競爭營的那個細胞去分裂以後
become four cells, then the composition of these four cells becomes a thin and wide
變成四個細胞,那這四個細胞組成變成一個感覺細寬
So this one feels pretty simple and we like doing pattern research with this
所以這個感覺很簡單,我們喜歡用這個做模式研究
because it's so simple, four cells
就是因為它非常簡單,四顆細胞
But there is a big problem here
可是這裡有一個很大的問題
the big problem is that
很大的問題就是說
These four cells are different
這四個細胞都不一樣
There is a cell that is responsible for growing the outer hair
有一個細胞呢,要負責長外面這個毛
Then there is a cell, which is supporting the structure of the hair
那有個細胞呢,是在支撐這個毛的結構
this orange cell
這個橘色的細胞
The structure that supports it is tilted up like this
在支撐它的這個翹起來這個結構這樣子
There's a nerve cell down there
那底下有一個神經細胞
green this is a nerve cell
綠色這是一個神經細胞
it wants to connect
它要連接
Its speed will connect to the muscles of the anal hairs
它這個速度會連接到肛毛的肌部
it can feel when the anal hairs move
它可以感受到肛毛動的時候
it has a signal to pass on
它就有訊號可以傳下去
Next to this nerve cell is another cell that protects it
那這神經細胞旁邊又有一個保護它的細胞
so you see 1234
所以你看到1234
that question
那這個問題
As far as we were studying cell division
就我們以前在學細胞分
Maybe everyone has studied biology in high school
也可能大家高中生物都有學過
One cell becomes two cells
細胞分的一顆細胞變兩顆細胞
Those two cells
那這兩顆細胞
will it be different
會不會變不一樣
we learned to say
我們學過說
A cell divides to become two different cells
一個細胞分裂變成兩顆不同的細胞
Then what we all read in the textbooks
那我們大家看的教科書上面畫的
Almost one cell becomes two cells
差不多是一個細胞變成兩個細胞
Two cells and then four cells
兩個細胞再經過有四顆細胞
The cells look exactly the same
這細胞長得一模一樣
but we know
可是我們知道說
What we have grown into today
我們今天發育成這個樣子
When we have so many different cells in our body
我們身上有這麼多不同的細胞的時候
Cells must become different during this process
這個過程細胞一定要變得不一樣
right
對不對
how to be different
怎麼變得不一樣
Then here is a very good example that says
那這裡提供一個非常好的例子就是說
its split in the middle
它的分裂中間
After splitting, or when splitting, you already know that you are going to be different
分裂完,或在分裂的時候,其實就已經知道自己要變得不一樣了
One cell becomes two cells, two cells are different
一個細胞變兩個細胞,兩個細胞就是不一樣
Well, how to achieve this? I let one cell divide and the two cells become different
好來,那這個怎麼達到說,我讓一個細胞分裂結束以後兩個細胞變得不一樣
It's an interesting subject
這是一個很有趣的課題
Then I will show you this, and you can take a look at the next one here
那我給大家看一下這個,下一張大家就可以看一下這裡
In fact, this is a bit like this, and it's also a bit like this
那其實這個有點像,也是有點這個
We can think of it as a concept of property
我們可以把它像是一個分財產的概念
When a parent distributes this property to two children, it can actually be divided differently
當一個父母親分給兩個小孩的這個財產其實可以分得不一樣
So we see that when the cell is about to divide
所以我們就看到說,這個細胞要分裂的時候
You see it's his, we say mitosis, spin down
你看到這是他的,我們說有絲分裂,紡垂絲
It's on the left and the right, you see the left and the right, this dyed protein is red
它在左邊跟右邊,你看到左邊跟右邊,這個染出來的蛋白質是紅色
This dyed protein is green
這染出來的蛋白質是綠色
The two are not the same, assigned to different proteins
兩個是不一樣的,分配到不一樣的蛋白質
So cells divide, so you see this side, right this movie
所以細胞分裂,所以你看到這邊,右邊這個電影
There are people in it that say, look, red and green
裡面有看到說,你看,紅色綠色
Green goes to one cell, red stays in another cell
綠色跑到一個細胞去紅色留在另外一顆細胞裡面
So this cell division actually seems to be
所以這個細胞分裂其實好像就是
I can assign different
我可以分配不同的
Properties assign different proteins to two different purple cells
財產分配不同的蛋白質給兩顆不同的紫細胞
and if your eyes
而且如果你眼睛
With a little effort, you can also notice that
力一點的話你還可以注意到說
This cell is relatively small, this cell is relatively large, right?
這個細胞比較小這個細胞比較大對不對
So our distribution can be divided and uneven
所以我們分配是可以分裂是可以不均勻的
unequal like this to split like this
不均等的這樣去分裂這樣子
so
所以
We can imagine that just now
我們就可以想像說剛剛
won
打贏了
After testing is
經過測議是
came out and won that cell
出來贏了那個細胞
The two cells can become different when it divides
它分裂的時候這兩顆細胞就可以變得不一樣
Because the assigned things are different
因為分到的東西不一樣
Then this cell is different when it divides
那這個細胞在分裂的時候又不一樣
This is not the same, which can constitute four different
這也不一樣那這可以構成四顆不同的
For purple cells, four cells are enough
這個紫細胞那是四顆細胞就可以
combined into one
結合在一起變成一個
sensory organs like this
感覺器官這樣子
Well, there is experimental evidence for this, for example,
那這個都是有實驗的證據的譬如說
we have some mutants
我們有一些突變種
that this
那這個
just won that cell if
剛剛贏了那顆細胞如果
split did not take place
分裂沒有進行
One of these proteins is missing the red green protein
其中有一個蛋白質這些蛋白質不見了紅色綠色蛋白質
You will find that it divides and produces two identical purple cells
你就會發現說它分裂以後產生兩顆一樣的紫細胞
It's not doing the so-called asymmetric cell division at this time
它這時候就沒有進行所謂不對稱的細胞分裂
Then when the cell divides again, there will be two identical cells again.
那這細胞再分裂又是兩顆一樣兩顆一樣這樣子
So this produces four cells that are exactly the same red
所以這產生四顆就是說一模一樣的紅色的細胞
Then in another mutant we saw that
那在另外一種突變種我們看到說
produced four nerve cells
產生了四顆神經細胞
Those horse babies outside are gone.
那外面那些馬娃什麼都不見了
so tell us here
所以這裡跟我們講說
There seems to be something quite unfair here
這裡好像有一個蠻不公平的現象
That is to say, when the cells divide, the substances that everyone distributes
就是說細胞在分裂的時候大家分配的物質
So this includes protein or RNA
那這包括蛋白質或者是RNA
Everyone is allocated different amounts
大家分配的不一樣多
So this cell inherits something different
所以這個細胞繼承的不一樣的東西
Of course, the direction of its subsequent development will be different.
它當然它的後面的發展的方向就不一樣
become different cells
就變成不同的細胞這樣子
OK
OK
No problem at all
當然沒問題
Then what I tell you now is very
那我現在跟大家講都是很
the feeling of something very unfair
一些很不公平的東西的感覺
who was born that gene
那天生誰基因
What protein to express inherits the expression at the beginning
要表達繼承要表達什麼蛋白質一開始的表達
proneuroelastin
原神經彈白質
Then go through this fierce competition
然後要經過這個激烈的競爭
And then finally distributed unequal
然後最後又分配了不均等
And then there is only one cell at the end
然後這個最後才有一個細胞
win out into nerve cells
勝出變成神經細胞
Then everything else becomes like this non-nerve cell
那其他都變成這個非神經細胞這樣子
That's the fact that we're
那可是事實上我們在
But now it's the reverse example
不過現在講過來是倒過來的例子
That is to say, in the whole developmental process
就是說其實在整個發育過程中
Sometimes we see cells that actually cooperate
有時候我們看到細胞事實上是有合作的
cooperate with each other
互相合作
then hand in hand then together
然後手牽手然後一起
to line up and then to make this last
來排列然後來造成這個最後一個
A developmental process looks like this
一個發育的過程這樣子
And they also have some so-called altruistic behaviors
而且他們還有一些所謂的利他的行為
it means i would rather sacrifice myself
就是說我寧願犧牲自己
Dedicated to this society
為了這個社會奉獻這樣子
So the other side of the example we are looking at now is that
所以我們現在看的另外一面的例子就是說
a wonderful society
一個美好的社會
what does cell society look like
細胞社會它的樣子是怎麼樣
Then this is from this
那這個是要從這個
Deputy Speech of State Operations
國營的副演講起
You may have seen a lot of state-run assistant actors.
那國營的副演大家可能看很多
this is very neat
這個非常整齊
Then this state-run deputy actor is different from our human eyes
那這個國營的副演跟我們人的眼睛不一樣
Small eyes make up 800
小眼睛構成800顆
small eyes
小眼睛的
very neatly arranged
排列得非常整齊
then i will always be in
那我就常常在
ask students to say
問學生說
how do you use when things are neatly arranged
你怎麼用當東西排列得非常整齊
How to make it line up very neatly
什麼方法讓它排列得非常整齊
the first one is to say
那第一個就是說
Because we used to live in the dormitory of the central courtyard
因為我們以前住在中央院宿舍
often hear this
常常聽到這個
When Hu Shiguo offered small favors
胡適國小招惠的時候
Some people say it's on par
就有人說 像中看齊
Then all students will
然後大家學生就會
align in the image and arrange
像中看齊 排列好
So one possibility is how
所以一種可能就是怎麼樣
Everyone is here, line up
大家就在這裡 排排站
Finally a signal came, everyone said
最後有個訊號過來 大家說
Everyone look up, everyone look up, right?
大家看齊 大家看齊 對不對
This is a way to arrange
這是一種排列的方式
that another
那另外一種
Of course, some people will be more clear that is to say
當然有一些人會比較清楚的就是說
like a crystalline way
像一個結晶的方式
We know that crystallization often has a seed crystal
我們知道結晶的話 常常有一個晶種
Then there may be a first stroke from the middle
然後可能從中間有一個先行程
then slowly
然後慢慢的
Slowly stack up one by one
慢慢的一顆一顆疊上去
Then we can fold very neatly
那我們就可以疊得非常整齊
like the process of crystallization
就像結晶的過程一樣
It can be arranged one by one
它就可以排列一個一個排列上去
Then we can imagine
然後我們就可以想像中說
there may be two ways
可能有兩種方式
can make this sure eye
可以讓這個果然的眼睛
The recovery is very neatly arranged like this
復原排列得非常整齊這樣子
Our experiment is to say that
我們的實驗就是覺得說
There may be a third way
可能或許有第三種方式
This eye developed from this piece
這個眼睛是從這一片發育過去的
After development, you see this area becomes like this
發育過去,你看到這一片變成這個樣子
you can see say
你可以看到說
You can imagine that this row of cells
你可以想像說這一排細胞
express a very specific gene like this
表達一個非常特別的基因這樣子
we found that
我們發現說
can't do this
搞不好這個
According to the research findings of many people
就很多人的研究發現說
This process is actually not the two ways we mentioned earlier.
這個過程其實不是我們前面講的那兩種樣子
But the third way is to say
而是第三種樣子就是說
One way you can do that is
你可以有一個方式就是
Can be arranged in a row-by-row manner
可以排列一排一排的方式
Then we see this row means that
那我們看到這一排的意思就是說
The development of this eye is not actually a start
這個眼睛的發育其實不是一顆開始
Then everyone holidays way
然後大家節間方式
not all together
也不是大家一起出現
And above is row by row
而上是一排一排過去
Then this looks like everyone went to the beach to watch the waves
那這個像好像大家到海邊去看海浪這樣子
float over like this
漂過來這樣子
a slope like this
一個坡這樣子
so it starts from here
所以它就是從這邊開始
Wave by wave, wave by wave
一波過去,一個波一個波過去
Then everyone will line up
然後大家就會排列
How to arrange this? Actually
那這怎麼排列呢?其實
The theory we put forward is that
這個我們提出的理論就是說
As long as you have one row, the previous row is neat
你只要有一排,上一排是整齊的
Suppose we could say something like
假設說我們可以講一句說
If everyone is in order in this row
這一排的位置,大家都是整齊的話
As for the people in the next row, just follow
那下一排的人呢,只要跟
Just wipe the gap between the two people in the front row
前一排的兩個人中間去擦那個縫隙就好
so you know what i mean
這樣知道我意思
I say what the next row will show up
我說下一排人出現的話
The next row is arranged first, how about the second row?
下一排先排好,那第二排人怎麼排?
Just wipe the gap between the two people in front of the first row
就是在第一排前面兩個人中間擦縫隙
So we see that there seems to be this smell here
所以我們看到說,這裡好像有這個味道
You see that this row of cells
你看到說這一排細胞
Then the next row of cells
然後下一排細胞
It seems that the cells are spaced in the middle
好像細胞都是間隔在中間的這樣子
So what we say is
所以我們的講法就是說
As long as the first row of cells is neat
你只要前一排細胞是整齊的話
Then the next row is neatly looking at the gaps of the previous row and rubbing in.
那下一排都整齊的看著前一排的縫隙擦進去
Then it can be neatly followed, right?
那就可以跟著整齊了對不對?
Row after row can be very neat like this
那一排一排一排都可以很整齊這樣子
So it's a simple idea
所以這是一個簡單的想法
There is a problem here, how to form the first row
這個出現一個問題,第一排怎麼形成
How do you have the neatness in the first row
你怎麼有第一排的整齊
In fact, we can see this
那其實這個我們可以看說
This is what I imagined
這個是我自己想像的
No, not necessarily experimentally verified
沒有,不一定有實驗證
You just said it looked like this
你剛才說這個像這個樣子
Then you only need one in the first row
那你第一排只要一顆就好
Then one of course is very neat with itself
然後一顆當然就自己跟自己是非常整齊
For the second row, there are two, right?
那第二排的話就兩顆對不對
It's far behind him, there are only three in the third row
跟他差開了,第三排就三顆
Then get away from those two
然後跟那兩顆差開
In addition to saying, we can imagine saying
那除了說,我們就可以想像說
As long as one row is neat, the next row will be uneven
只要一排整齊,下一排差風齊
just follow neatly
就跟著整齊一過去
Like a wave of cell division
像是有一波細胞分化的過程
that goes all the way from the back to the front
那一直從後面到前面
Then it can be worth this at the beginning
那就可以抵定這個一開始
Roughly arranged in the way
大致上排列的方式
Then everyone can have a neat one
那大家就可以有一個整齊的一個
Arranged like this
排列方式這樣子
OK
OK
this is
這個是
Of course, this has not been confirmed in many places.
這個當然很多地方還沒有證實
But this is an interesting idea like this
不過這個是一個有趣的想法這樣子
There are still some in this process
那這個過程中還有一些
movement of cell populations
細胞群體的運動的方式
I find this very interesting
這個我覺得很有意思
If you watch this sub-act
如果大家看這個副演
This is the sub-actor and this is sliced
這個是副演這個做切片
You slice him sideways like this
你給他做側面切片這樣子
sliced ​​like this
切片出來是這個樣子
inside the slice if you look at it with one of the eyes
切片裡面如果你拿其中一個眼睛來看的時候
you see it becomes like this
你看它就變成這個樣子
This is the photoreceptor cell
這是感光細胞
it has a
它有一個
An arrangement of P-type
P型的一個排列方式
P type arrangement
P型排列方式
you all look carefully
你們大家仔細看
when you look at this one
那你看這一張的時候
Do you feel that other places are different
有沒有覺得其他有什麼地方不一樣
yes someone saw it
對 有人看到了
up and down are mirror images
上下是鏡像
So the T-shape above looks like this
所以上面的T型是這個樣子
The following T shape looks like this
下面的T型是這個樣子
The sharper places are this one facing down and this one facing up
比較尖的地方是這個朝下 這個朝上
How did this come about?
那這個到底怎麼達到的
Because we just said that its differentiation process is from behind
因為我們剛剛說它的分化過程是從後面
keep going forward row by row
一直往前一排一排過去的
Then there seems to be a line somewhere in the middle
然後似乎在中間的地方有一條線
separate it
把它分開來
up and down this
上下的這個
This group of cells will do different exercises
這個一群一群的細胞就要做不同的運動
Therefore, in the research here, many people have found that
所以這裡的研究很多人研究就發現說
In fact, there is actually a group of cells together
其實這裡事實上是有一個一群細胞一起
a process of rotation
旋轉的一個過程
We see that the above cells are rotating clockwise
我們看到說上面細胞就是順時鐘的旋轉
The cells below are rotating counterclockwise
下面細胞就是逆時鐘的旋轉
So we can form up and down this
所以可以構成上下這個
There is an arrangement of mirror images like this
有一個鏡像的一個排列的方式這樣子
So the formation of this ghost silver eye it neatly lined up
所以這個鬼銀的眼睛的形成它整齊排列
In fact, this process is quite a lot
其實是蠻多的這個過程
Now let's talk about the third process
那現在要講第三個過程
The fourth process is actually
第四個過程其實是
Quite a special process of standing and collapsing
蠻特別的一個立塌的過程
that is
就是說
Finally, to form a very neat monocular
最後要形成一個非常整齊的一個單眼
Each single eye should be very neat and fixed.
這每個單眼都要很整齊很固定的樣子
In the end, a very good structure can be formed
最後才能形成一個非常好的一個結構
But in the process of development
可是在發育過程中
Often a strategy is to say
常常有一個策略就是說
Your whole eye has 800 small eyes
你這整個眼睛800個小眼
If each small-eyed character has 20 cells
每個小眼角色有20顆細胞的話
how many cells do you need
你需要多少細胞
800 times 20
800乘以20
right
對不對
This is 16000 cells
這個是16000個細胞
That's how many times it takes for a cell to divide
那可是細胞分裂要分裂多少次
will reach 16,000 cells
會達到16000個細胞
Then cell division can be controlled so precisely
然後細胞分裂可以控制得那麼準
Generated exactly 16,000 cells
剛好產生16000個細胞
actually not
其實是不行的
So the development strategy is often
所以發展的策略常常是
We often see a developmental strategy that says
我們常常看到一個發育的策略就是說
We'd rather do more first
我們寧願先多做一些
Let's make 20,000 cells
我們做個2萬個細胞好了
18000 cells are good
18000個細胞好了
we would rather have more
我們寧願多一點
but not less
但是不要少
that's a little more
那多一點
but more is good
可是多一點是好的
but there will be problems
可是會有問題
For example, we see
譬如說我們看到說
during development
在發育過程
24 hours
24小時的時候
The arrangement is not neat
排列是不整齊的
Especially the outermost circle
尤其是最外圈這一圈
There seem to be many more cells
細胞好像多了不少個
and then 24 hours later
然後再過24小時之後
neatly arranged
排列很整齊
In fact, there is a cell in the middle
其實這中間有一個細胞的
The process of the wither
凋王的過程
That is to say, it is ugly
也就是說講難聽一點
If there are too many cells, they will die.
細胞多了就去死吧
just die
就死掉
So in fact some cells in the middle
所以事實上這中間有些細胞就背
a signal appears
一個訊號出現
There is a signal in the middle
這中間有一個訊號的出現
Then put the next cell
然後就把旁邊的細胞
let it do this withering
讓它進行這個凋網
So this cell
那所以說這個細胞
Just the right number will be left
就會剩下剛剛好的數字
Then form a grid of gold grids like this
然後形成一格一格的這個金格這樣子
Then we can see that
那我們可以看到說
If the withering network of the cell is
如果細胞的這個凋網要是
when it didn't happen
沒有發生的時候
In fact, the eyes began to appear some
其實眼睛就開始出現一些
The messy phenomenon is like this
雜亂的現象這樣子
or hypercellularity
或過多細胞過多
or irregular arrangement
或排列不整齊的現象
So this we can say
所以這個我們可以說
It's an act of setting it up
這是一個立它的行為
some cells during development
有些細胞在發育過程中
when its function has ended
當它的功能已經結束了
or when it is not needed
或不需要它的時候
Or just after the temporary function ends
或者是只是暫時性的功能結束以後
then it is possible to carry out the withering of cells
那它就是可能要進行細胞的凋網
Then just for the sake of this perfect state of the whole society
然後就為了整個社會的這個完美這樣子
OK
OK
So this is the second part of what I'm going to say
那這是我要講的第二部分就是說
In addition to the competitive behavior we talked about at the beginning, cells
細胞除了一開始我們講的競爭的行為
The second part is that cells also cooperate
那第二部分就是細胞也有合作的
make it act
立它的行為
Then I will now enter the third topic
那我現在進入第三個主題
This is quite an interesting story
這個是蠻有趣的故事
i often like to say this
我常常喜歡講這個
I would like to put my research under an interesting topic
我會想把我的研究放到一個有趣的題目下面去講
So this tells the story first
所以這個先講這個故事
it's an interesting story
這個蠻有趣的故事
Maybe some of you have also heard this story on the Internet
可能有些人也聽過這個故事在網路上
can also be seen
也可以看得到
Or I wrote about it in House Weekly
或者我在眾院的周刊也寫過這個報導
that is
就是說
Here is a study in London, UK
這有一個英國倫敦的一個研究
Many people may have traveled to London
很多人可能去過倫敦旅遊
know that london is a very old city
知道倫敦是一個非常古老的城市
There's a big problem with this ancient city
這古老城市有一個很大的麻煩
That is to say, its roads have been messed up for hundreds of years
就是說它幾百年來它的道路就是亂七八糟的
We saw it said in an area next to a train station
我們看到說在一個火車站旁邊的一個區域
you see this area
你看到這個區域
see this yellow is the big road
看到這個黃色是大的馬路
It doesn't love the way of mental peace like our lieutenant colonel
它就沒有不像我們的中校人愛心理和平的路
very straight like this
很直這樣子
it's messed up like this
它就亂七八糟這樣子
Then you should not ignore that there are many small roads inside.
那你更不要忽略到裡面有很多細細小小的路
very very complicated
非常非常複雜
then we know this
那我們知道這個
Immigrants in the UK are probably different from us
英國的入民大概跟我們不一樣
We like to use Zhongxiao East Road Section 1 Section 2 Section 3 Section 4 Section 5
我們喜歡用中校東路一段二段三段四段五段
It's easy to remember, right?
很好記對不對
Each of their roads may be called a name for a small section
他們的每一條路可能小小一段就叫一個名字
A short paragraph is called a name
小小一段就叫一個名字
So there is a big problem here, that is,
所以這個出現一個很大的問題就是說
What to do with inheritance car drivers in London
倫敦的繼承車司機怎麼辦
There may be tens of thousands of paths
它這個可能有幾萬條路
Then there may be thousands of attractions
然後可能有上千個景點
Then inherit the car driver
然後繼承車司機
Let me tell you which road I want to go to, a certain scenic spot
我跟你說我要去哪一條路的某一個景點
it's about to know
它馬上就要知道
This study was before GPS
這個研究是在GPS出現之前
so let's talk
所以先講好
Now that the GPS comes out, of course this problem will be gone.
現在GPS出來以後當然這問題就沒了
So we know that some people are very good at recording
所以說我們知道說人有些人很會記錄
you just talk to him
你只要跟他講一下
He knew right away how to get there
他馬上就知道怎麼去怎麼過去
That is to say, we know that he is old
那就是說我們知道說他道老裡面那個
The so-called Name-A-Gation means
那個所謂的Name-A-Gation就是說
The concept of controlling space in space is very good
在空間駕馭空間的概念非常的好
He knew right away how to get there
他馬上就知道怎麼過去
Which road is the fastest way to go recently?
哪一條路最近怎麼走最快這樣子
London heritage car drivers have a very special
倫敦繼承車司機有一種很特別的
it is more black
它比較Black
black cab driver black cab driver
黑計程車司機 黑設計程車司機
They need special training
他們是需要經過專門的訓練
They can't just say they want to be taxi drivers
他們不可能隨便說要當計程車司機
be a taxi driver
就當計程車司機
Because this road is too complicated
因為這個路實在是太複雜
So their training is actually
所以他們的訓練其實是
like we go to college
就像我們念大學一樣
they say average training down
他們說平均訓練下來
to get this driver's license
要拿到這個駕駛執照
about two to four years
大概要兩年到四年的時間
two to four years
兩年到四年的時間
So it's not easy
所以是非常不簡單的
Then you have to go through a lot of exams in the middle
然後中間要經過很多的考試
The small test and the big test look like this
小考大考這樣子
In fact, many people fail
其實很多人失敗
No way to get this to drive like this
沒辦法拿到這個駕駛這樣子
During their training over the course of two to four years
他們在兩到四年的過程的訓練過程中
They feel as if we are studying
他們覺得好像是我們在念書一樣
We are learning a major
我們在學一個專業一樣
After two to four years, these people
那這些人兩到四年後
they feel like
他們就覺得說
This ability is definitely related to the ability to control space
這個能力絕對是跟空間駕馭的能力有關係
Spatial control
空間駕馭
For example, let me tell you now
譬如說我現在跟大家說
How to get to the Forbidden City
故宮怎麼去
can anyone get this right now
有誰可以馬上這個
report it to the boss
到老闆面反映出來
Maybe some people in there will know soon
可能裡面有些人很快就知道
from which road the whole past
從哪一條路整個過去
Then some people say I am GPS
那有些人說我GPS
I can't pass without me
不在身上沒辦法過去
this is
這個是
There is no space, there is no difference
就沒有空間就沒有不一樣
so they go and say
所以他們就去看說
Why do some people have this
為什麼有些人的這個
can pass this exam
可以通過這個考試
trained and passed the exam
經過訓練有通過考試
What the hell happened in his head
他到腦裡面到底發生了什麼事情
what's going on in the brain
到腦裡面到底發生什麼事情
they found out
他們發現說
in the hippocampus of the brain
在大腦一個海馬迴的地方
his back area
他的後區域
this place
這個地方
as long as you pass this exam
只要通過這個考試的
And especially the longer you drive
然後尤其是開車開越久
that area will get a little bit bigger
那個區域就會變大一點點
the back half of the hippocampus
那個海馬迴的後半部的地方
there will be a little
會有一點點
that use this
那個用這個
We call this image development
這個我們叫做影像顯影
this came out looking
這個出來看起來
It's really a little bigger
真的是比較大一點點
and this
而且這個
as long as you drive
你只要開得越久
more familiar people
越熟悉的人
the bigger the place
那個地方就越大
Then you go to see those who failed
那你去看那些失敗的
maybe a year and a half
可能進去一年半年
then what
然後什麼樣
that place didn't get bigger
那個地方就沒有變大
this place doesn't get any bigger
這個地方就沒有變大
this is very special
這個很特別
That is to say, there is a linear relationship between
就是說這個有一個線性的關係
say you are more familiar
說你越熟悉
the longer you train
你訓練越久
then you this
然後你這個
The longer you drive, the bigger your place will be
開的越久,那你這個地方就會變得越大
This increased size has something to do with it
這個增加的大小就跟它有關係
Then you lose no one
然後你失敗人就沒有
challenge
有人就提出挑戰
Said, maybe this is not related to the experience of driving a taxi
說,這個搞不好不是開計程車經驗的關係
And maybe this is just a London air move
而這個搞不好只是倫敦的空氣招啊
Work is stressful
工作壓力大啊
Then your place may have something to do with your resistance to stress
然後你那地方可能跟你的抗壓性有關
or something
或怎麼樣的
Then they study very simple
那他們就研究的很簡單
That's easy. I'll just find out the bus driver in London.
那很簡單我就把倫敦的公車駕駛找出來
That bus driver breathes dirty air every day.
那公車駕駛一樣每天吸著骯髒的空氣啊
And it's a lot of pressure every day.
然後每天這個有很大壓力啊
Let's look at this area of ​​their brain
那去看他們的大腦這個區域
no increase in
並沒有增加的現象
So in other words, this is driving a taxi
所以就是說,這個是開計程車
A special phenomenon of the driver is like this
司機特別的一個現象這樣子
Then they also put some
然後他們也把一些
Later, he stopped, and he said that I am in my 40s and I am going to retire.
後來不開了,他說我40幾歲我要退休了這樣子
Then you found out that the longer you retire
那你發現說退休越久
That place shrinks back a little bit like this
那個地方就縮小回去一點點這樣子
Obviously, that place has a very obvious relationship with the control of space.
就顯然那個地方跟空間的駕馭有一個很明顯的關係
this is an interesting report
這是一個很有趣的報導
Then everyone here says
然後這裡大家就說
what about london
那倫敦這樣子
Is there any in New York?
請問紐約有沒有
or does paris have
或巴黎有沒有
Will the genetic design of Taipei City look like this?
台北市的基因設計會不會這樣子
Does anyone know
有沒有人知道
In fact, if you go to New York or Paris or Taipei
那其實大家如果去紐約或巴黎或台北市
Our path is actually more
我們的道路其實是比較
Four squares, right?
四四方方對不對
especially new york
尤其紐約
And the roads in New York are pretty easy to remember, right?
而且紐約的道路非常好記對不對
12345678910 Pass like this
12345678910這樣過去
That 12345 looks like this
那12345這樣子
So their driver
所以他們的那個駕馭的
Your brain trains you to control this ability
你的大腦裡面訓練你駕馭的這個能力
There is no need to go to such a strong training like this
就不需要到那麼強的一個訓練這樣
So it can reflect that
所以可以反映說
To become a skill design in London
在倫敦裡面要變成一個技能設計
your training is very solid
你的訓練是非常扎實
then a certain area of ​​your brain
那你某些大腦裡面某一個區域
It really has something to do with space control
真的是跟空間駕馭有關係
Then after you enter the training
然後你進入過訓練以後
Your area will grow a little bit like this
你的區域就會變大一點點這樣子
So this in their same research
所以這個在他們用同樣研究
when looking in other cities
在別的城市看的時候
There is no such phenomenon in the ongoing period in other places.
其他地方的進行時期並沒有這個現象這樣子
It's an interesting subject
這是一個很有趣的一個題材
so why
所以為什麼
That actually has a price
那這個其實有代價
Let me tell you about this first
這個先跟大家講一下
In fact, many different industries
其實很多的不同行業
if you've been training somewhere
你一直在訓練某一個地方的話
There may be some changes in some parts of your brain
你大腦某些地方可能會有一些改變
some changes
一些改變
Is there a price for this change?
那這個改變有沒有代價
It means you are very good now
就是說你現在很會
When you become a professional taxi driver
你變成一個專業的計程車時期
Then you'll be able to know where to go
然後你很能夠知道去哪裡
Your ability to control space has improved
你的空間駕馭能力變很好
In fact, they found that
其實他們有發現說
Hey, the instant memory ability of these people for an image
欸這些人對一個影像的即時的記憶能力
In fact, there are a little worse than the average person
事實上是有比一般人差一點
when one of your abilities becomes stronger
就當你某一種能力變強的
help him use your nervous system
你的神經系幫他去用
When using this function
用這個某一個功能的時候
Some of your other abilities may disappear like this
你其他的能力可能就會消失掉一些這樣子
That's quite an interesting way of saying it.
這是蠻有趣的一個講法
That
那
How did the brain change?
那大腦到底是怎麼產生什麼樣的變化
Why is it about remembering something
那為什麼在於記憶某些東西
Then it will make a slight change somewhere in you like this
然後就會讓你的某個地方稍微發生改變這樣子
Well, there's actually a theory
那其實這有一個理論
What this theory actually says is
那這個理論其實講的是
Yeah, it's worth mentioning that these people aren't young people or kids.
對 還得要提的就是這些人不是年輕人也不是小孩子
We know that the brains of children or young adults may still be developing, so it changes like this
我們知道小孩子或年輕人大腦可能還在發育啊 變化這樣子
But these adults are in their twenties
可是這些成人都二十幾歲了
The brain is actually quite fixed like this
大腦其實蠻固定的這樣子
But there will still be some changes
可是還是會產生一些變化
How did this change come about?
那這個變化到底怎麼來
We are saying that our memories have a structural plasticity
我們就是說我們的記憶有一種結構的可塑性
The credibility of the structure means that its structure can still be changed
結構的可信就是說還是可以去改變它的結構
when we remember something
我們記一個東西的時候
This thing if we go through many times of training
這個東西如果我們經過多次的訓練
I remember when I was very familiar
記得很熟悉的時候
There may be a structural change
可能就會產生一個結構上的變化
The structure is generally the change in the synapse we just talked about
那個結構上一般則是我們剛剛講的突觸上的變化
A synapse is where two nerve cells meet
突觸就是兩個神經細胞接觸的地方
Right, the place where the axon meets the tachyon just mentioned
對不對 剛剛講的軸突跟速突交接的地方
synaptic changes
突觸的變化
Then there is a meaning map
那這是有一個思義圖
For example, the junction of these two nerve cells
譬如說這兩個神經細胞的交接的地方
this prominent place
這突出的地方
Then there are some molecular mechanisms here that we won't talk about
那這裡有一些分子機制我們就不講
It is possible that the protrusion will become larger
它就可能這個突出就會變大
or split into two
或者分裂變成兩個
touch more strongly
接觸得更強烈一點
tighter
更緊實一點
it can make a dramatic difference
它可以造成突出的變化
So how do we do this experiment?
那我們實驗是怎麼做這種實驗
In fact, ours is actually a small experiment.
其實我們這個其實是小小的實驗
But I also thought it was an interesting experiment
可是我那時候也覺得滿有趣的一個實驗
Of course we can't make it too complicated
就是當然我們不可能去做太複雜
We're going to use this larva of the fruit fly
我們就利用果蠅的這個幼蟲
If you can see this
大家如果看得到這個
here is one
這裡有一隻
Did you notice the difference between the two larvae?
有沒有注意到這兩隻幼蟲的差別
Let's take a look again
大家再看一下
is there one here
這裡有一隻有沒有
little bit
小小的一點
here is one
這裡有一隻
This one runs fast
它這一隻跑得很快
Something at the same time came here
同一個時間的東西跑到這裡來
It seems that this one is not willing to climb
它這一隻好像不太願意爬
in place like this
就在原地這樣子
Then we found out that
那我們就發現說
These larvae crawl slowly like this
這些幼蟲爬得慢的慢慢爬的這樣子
it's this prominent
它的這個突出
It is easier for the motor nerve cells to protrude from the inner surface of the muscle
運動神經細胞跟肌肉的內面突出就長得比較簡單一點
But if this larva that's been crawling very fast
但是如果一直爬得很快的這種幼蟲
Its prominence will grow a little more complicated
它的突出就會長得比較複雜一點
And this sure enough larva research is relatively simple
而且這個果然的幼蟲研究比較簡單
That means we only have to do it for about 8 hours
就是說我們只要做大約8個小時的時間
we saw that
我們就看到說
Already crawling fast and crawling slowly stand out
已經爬得快了跟爬得慢的突出的
There is a big difference in this growth ratio, like this
這個生長的比例就有一個蠻大的差異這樣子
This means that after we become adults,
這個就是說其實我們變成一個成人以後
Our brains are still somewhat forgiven
我們大腦還是有些可恕性
when you have been training in a certain place
那你是一直訓練在某一個地方的時候
The power of your place will become stronger
你那地方的能力就會變強
But at the same time it is possible that some will lose
但是同時有可能有一些會失去這樣子
Everything is the same
這個所有東西都是一樣的這樣子
This is a very important concept to tell you about
這是一個很重要的跟大家講突出的概念
In fact, our brains have just started talking about a lot of protruding things.
其實我們大腦裡面剛一開始講了非常非常多的突出
There are more than 14 protrusions in a brain
一個大腦裡面有14方以上的突出
Those highlights are recording our life
那些突出就是在記錄我們生活上的
Bit by bit like this
點點滴滴這樣子
your life experience what you remember
你的生活經驗 你記憶下來的東西
That's a lot, it's like one
那很多的 這好像就是一個
A previous recorder
一個以前的這個recorder
What is this called, a flow machine or something?
這個叫什麼 流生機或什麼的
You record it, every time you experience something
你就記錄在裡面 那你每次經歷過一個事情
You might just record these things in there
你可能就把這些事情記錄在裡面
Then you just remember to call it out next time like this
那你就記得下次就可以把它叫出來這樣子
OK, it's as if our brain has a record of this
OK 就好像我們大腦有一個記錄這種
So the highlight of this new Labs is
那所以說這個新Labs突出就是
It may be that we accumulate various experiences in our brains
可能是我們大腦裡面累積各種經驗
Memories, so if you listen to me today
記憶的東西 所以今天如果大家聽完我的
Speech and then if you remember the representative said
演講 然後如果還記得的話代表說
I've left some notes in your salient
我已經在你的突出裡面留下一些記錄了
then this is
那這個就
that last
那最後
to mention
要提到
We're actually a favorite subject of late
我們實際上是最近比較喜歡的課題
That's the one from Sudo
就是速突的這個
Variety
變化
Diversity and complexity
多樣性還有複雜性
Diversity goes without saying
多樣性不用講
We've just emphasized a lot
我們剛已經強調很多
look at every nerve cell
你看每一個神經細胞
this ontology
這個本體
We started with nerve cells
我們開始講的神經細胞
ontology
本體
this is its speed
這是它的速度
Each speed grows very
每個速度都長得非常
very big difference
差異非常大
look different
樣子都不一樣
This is basically defined
這是基本上定義的
each nerve cell
每個神經細胞
different kinds
不同的種類
This also has a lot to do with its function
這也跟它的功能有很大的關係
look different
長得不一樣
Its function may be different
它的功能可能就不太一樣
this
這個
In our four nerves
我們的四神經裡面
actually a lot
其實就很多
this kind of
這類的這個
speed
速度
it has some features
它有一些特性
For example, we can see that
譬如說我們可以看到說
exist
在
inside the eyeball
眼球裡面
The speed of the four nerves
這個四神經的這個速度
you see say
你看到說
One by one is actually arranged
一顆一顆其實是排列的
fairly neat
還算滿整齊的
and you feel like it has
而且你覺得它好像有
certain one
一定的一個
a sense of domain
一個領域的感覺
have their own field
自己有自己的領域
this one
這一顆
with this one
跟這一顆
probably a certain one
大概有一定的一個
a distance like this
一個距離這樣子
Then everyone has a
然後大家都有一個
one
一個
a speed
一個速度
such a certain field
這麼某一個領域這樣子
We know that our eyes need to sense a few things
我們知道我們眼睛需要感覺幾個東西
One is to feel the color, right?
一個就是感覺這個顏色 對不對
The second is to feel a type, a pattern, and a contrast
第二要感覺一個型、一個pattern、一個反差
or a boundary line
或者一個界線、線條
when we see something
我們看到一個東西的時候
where or how its boundaries
它的界線在哪裡或怎樣
The third thing to probably look at is a sporty
第三個可能要看的就是一個運動的
movement of things
東西的運動的樣子
You can talk about our vision mirror
我們這種視認鏡你可以講一下說
It may have something to do with where something is in space
它可能跟一些東西在空間的位置有關係
It's the kind of neuron that fills the entire eye
它這類的神經元佈滿整個眼睛的
covered with these dendrites
佈滿這些樹突
These dendrites can be quite funny sometimes
這些樹突有時候還蠻有趣的
It has something to do with the directionality of the movement of the objects that my eyes see
它跟我眼睛看的物體移動的方向性有關係
We can have fun looking at the example
我們可以看這個例子很有趣
if you look carefully
如果大家仔細看的話
One by one nerve cells can be seen
可以看得出來一顆一顆神經細胞
You see the body of the cell, right?
你看到這細胞的本體對不對
Ontology we just talked about
我們剛剛講的本體
This is an axon, a very long axon
這個是軸突、非常長的軸突
The axons of each nerve cell gather to
每一顆神經細胞的軸突都聚集到
go to the same place
同一個地方去
it this gathers together
它這個聚集會一起
extend into the brain
延伸到大腦裡面去
Another interesting thing is that this tree diagram
另外有趣的就是說這個樹圖
look at this tree diagram
你看這個樹圖
Notice the consistency of these tree diagrams
有沒有注意到這些樹圖的一致性
how are they
它們都怎麼樣
It's all down and down
都是往下的往下藻
So you should be able to guess what the function of this thing is
所以大家應該可以猜得到這個東西的功能是什麼
It may have something to do with detecting the direction of movement of objects outside
可能跟偵測外面的物體的移動的方向有關係
Then their research thinks that
那他們的研究覺得說
This may have something to do with the direction some objects are running up
這可能跟一些物體往上跑的方向有關係
So within these four nerves
所以在這個四神經之裡面
It can be seen that there are four kinds of trees, and some tree diagrams are the group that goes down.
可以看到有四種有些樹圖是往下的這一群
Some are to the right, some are to the left, some are up
那有些是往右有些是往左有些是往上
So at least basically we can detect some different directions
所以至少基本上我們可以偵測一些不同的方向
Let's go back to this dissatisfaction
那我們先回到這個不滿
nerve cells of dissatisfaction
這種不滿性的神細胞
So of course we're doing this experiment with fruit flies.
那我們當然是用果蠅在做這個實驗
What about the fruit fly?
那這個果蠅的話
We saw that it was a larva
我們看到說這是一隻幼蟲
Then from the nerve cells in the body
那又從身上的這種神細胞
You see, this is the body one by one
你看這是本體一顆一顆一顆一顆
But its speed is not enough for the whole body
可是它的速度就不滿全身
You see this speed everywhere
你看到到處都有這個速度
I often feel like the larva is wearing a gold and aluminum coat
我常常覺得幼蟲好像穿了一個金鋁衣一樣
Dissatisfied with the whole body like this
不滿全身這樣子
This has a lot to do with the larva's ability to sense external stimuli.
這個跟幼蟲去感應外面的刺激有很大的關係
This is mainly the induction of two stimuli
這個主要是感應兩種刺激
It's a nerve limb called pain sensation
它是一種叫做痛覺的神經緣
feel something harmful
感覺到一些有害的
Harmful stimuli from the outside world
外界來有害的刺激
one is high temperature
一個是高溫
For example, if the temperature is higher than 45 degrees
比如說溫度高到45度以上
You pierce it with a needle at 45 degrees
這個你用45度的一個針去刺它
you'll find that the larvae will roll to the other side
你就會發現說幼蟲會滾往另外一邊
it has a scrolling behavior
它有一個滾動的行為
It can also feel strong light
它還可以感受到強光
When stimulated by strong light, it will run in the other direction
強光一刺激以後它就會往另外一方向跑
So we can know that
所以我們就可以知道說
These speeds of the nerve serve two functions
神經的這些速度有兩個功能
One is to feel harmful
一個就是要感覺有害的
second what else do you know
第二個還要知道什麼
Is the direction of stimulation coming from right?
刺激來的方向對不對
That's why you know what I want
所以你才知道說我要怎麼樣
I'm going to run to the other side
我要往另外一邊跑
so show everyone this
所以給大家看這個
a movie
一個movie
This is always climbing
這是一直又從在爬喔
Did you see that strong light stimulated it?
你看到啊 強光刺激它有沒有
It escaped and crawled to the other side
它就躲掉了 往另外一邊爬
ok let's see again
好 我們再看一次
it crawls to the right
它往右邊爬
Then suddenly a
然後突然出現一個
glare
強光
it just avoids that direction
它就往躲開那個方向
So you could conceivably say
所以你可以想像說
Its whole body is covered with this
它整個身體布滿了這種
This is what it says is a harmful irritant
這是它對它講是一個有害的刺激的
a source of
的一個來源
Because the larva under the strong light
因為強光下這個幼蟲
May be sun-dried
可能會被曬成乾喔
dry it and it may die
曬成乾它就可能死掉
It must have this sure-fire larva
它必須要 這個果然的幼蟲
may have to hide in food
可能要躲在食物裡面
Then a humid environment like this
然後一個潮濕的環境這樣子
so it body it except
所以它身體 它除了
I know it's harmful
知道說這個是有害之外
The way it needs to know the source of this light
它要知道這個光的來源的方式
So it covers the whole body when it is actually projected to the central nervous system
所以它佈滿了全身其實就是在這個投射到中樞神經的時候
It actually has a proper alignment
它事實上是有一個適當的排列
Then you can know where the stimulus is coming from
那可以知道刺激從哪邊來
The research in our laboratory is actually to study several topics of this speed.
那我們實驗室的研究其實是研究這個速度的幾個題目
Then I will try to give a few interesting examples like this
那我會盡量講幾個有趣的例子這樣子
In fact, we used a lot of relatively high-end microscopes
其實我們用了很多比較高階的顯微鏡
You can see that this rate of growth has been moving
你可以看到這個速度的生長一直在動
In fact, we can imagine that it is actually very similar to human beings.
這個事實上我們可以想像說其實就跟人也很像
Our speed is actually the speed inside the body may be growing all the time
我們的速度其實是身體裡面的速度可能一直在生長
It's always changing, it's always moving around like this
一直在不斷的變化一直在動來動去這樣子
Then our microscope can see the movement of some molecules in the speed
那我們的顯微鏡可以去看速度裡面的一些分子的運動情況
Then let's slowly tell some interesting stories like this
那我們就慢慢講幾個有趣的故事這樣子
Let's look at this first
那我們先看這一張
Let's take pictures of the dynamics at this speed
我們拍這個速度的動態的樣子
Did you see any behavior
那你們有沒有看到什麼樣的行為
Actually, we saw how some dendrites
其實我們看到說有些樹突怎麼樣
is extending
是在延伸的
how about some
有些怎麼樣
shrinking
在收縮
Some of them are newborns
那有些是新生出來了
Actually, one thing I find interesting is the behavior of repulsion
其實有一個我覺得有趣的是排斥的行為
everyone can see
大家可以看到
Both dendrites want to grow
這兩棵樹突都想長出來
Then what if they bump into each other
然後都碰到彼此就怎麼樣
retracted
就縮回去了
You know, these dendrites all come out of the same nerve cell.
要知道說這些樹突都是從同一個神經細胞出來的
You think it's the body of the same nerve cell
你想到這是同一個神經細胞的本體
Then keep branching and branching
然後一直分岔一直分岔
then come out
然後出來
The growth of the dendrites
那這個樹突的生長
it has two principles
它有兩個原則
There are two principles
有兩個原則
Just now you saw the amount of dendrites that were dissatisfied from birth
就剛剛大家看到那個又從生上不滿的樹突的量
It is so long there are two principles
它這樣長有兩個原則
one is to say how
一個就是說怎麼樣
It wants to dissatisfy the whole body as much as possible
它想要盡量去不滿全身
because you can't have a body have a place
因為你不能有一個身體有一個地方
without that dendrite
沒有那個樹突
Then if the other side is exposed to high temperature or high
那這樣子那邊要是被高溫或高
If you are stimulated by the high gun light, you will not feel it
高槍光刺激到的話你就感覺不到
that's dangerous
那就危險了
So you have to find a way to increase the speed all the time
所以你要想辦法去速度一直長一長一長
fill all the space like this
填滿所有的空間這樣子
So it's this velocity that we call space filling
所以這是一種我們把它叫做空間填滿的這種速度
That is to say, where there is space, it will quickly extend it.
就是說有空間的地方它就趕快去延伸過去
and then want to fill it up
然後就想要去把它填滿
what about the second one
第二個是怎麼樣
it has an evasive behavior
它有一個躲避的行為
That is to say, it does not need two speeds in the same space
就是說當它同一個空間不需要兩根速度
touch together intertwine
碰在一起交錯在一起
then go fill it
然後去填滿它
So often two speeds
所以常常兩根速度
What happens when two speeds of the same nerve cell collide
同一個神經細胞兩根速度碰在一起的時候怎麼樣
it shrank
它就萎縮了
One shrank or both shrank
有一根也萎縮或兩根萎縮掉
Because I don't want to cover the same place over and over again
因為我不要去重複地去佈滿同一個地方
Then you can imagine that this is the most economical
那大家可以想像說這是一個最經濟
Either the most efficient or a
或者是最有效或者是一個
You have to try to fill all the space
你要盡量去佈滿所有的空間
But what if we don't want to have two speeds?
可是我們又不希望有兩個速度怎麼樣
touch together and then this
碰在一起然後就這個
to intertwine
去交錯在一起
This is a study, that is, this space-filled neuron
這是一個研究,就是說這種空間佈滿的神經原
Then they will grow a lot of soil, and then try to fill this space as much as possible
然後他們就會長出很多的宿土,然後想儘量去佈滿這個空間
But they try not to touch each other
可是他們又盡量不碰在一起
So here's a picture, a sure enough picture kind of
所以這裡有一個圖片,一個果然圖片種
Then you can see that many places are intertwined with each other.
那你就看到說好多地方宿土都交錯在一起
These two stick together
這兩根黏在一起
Then some years form a handful, these two stick together
那有些年成一小撮,這兩根黏在一起
Do you have a serious habit?
有沒有非常嚴重的宿土的
They mean that when they meet together
他們就是說他們碰在一起以後
They don't know to separate
他們便不知道要分開
together after we meet
碰在一起以後就在一起
OK, so let’s ask, how does a normal dweller know
OK,所以我們就問說,那正常的宿土怎麼知道
avoidance
迴避,自我迴避
We are talking about this now, and we are very particular about avoiding self-interest.
我們現在講這個,講究的非常厲害,自我利益的迴避
To know how to avoid yourself like this, how does Sutu avoid yourself
要懂得自我迴避這樣子,那宿土怎麼樣去迴避自己
Then this is a very interesting mutation
那這個是一個非常有趣的一個突變
This gene is called Beware of the Sale of Schimarchy
這個基因叫做當心的Sale of Schimarchy
just a soup
就是一個湯
It is neutralizing positive cell skin molecules like this
是中和正的細胞臨膚分子這樣子
it's a gene
這是一個基因
This gene can make 40,000 proteins
這個基因可以做4萬個蛋白質出來
One gene makes 40,000 proteins
一個基因做4萬個蛋白質
the funny thing is to say
有趣的地方就是說
It's inside every nerve cell
它在每一個神經細胞裡面
The expressed protein is different
表達的蛋白質是不一樣的
This is because gene splicing
這是因為經過基因的剪接
one gene can make
一個基因就可以做出
But it's inside every nerve cell
可是它在每一個神經細胞裡面
The expressed molecules are different
表達的分子都不一樣
Because different splicing is different
因為經過不同的剪接都不一樣
So you could conceivably say
所以你可以想像說
Each nerve cell expresses only a specific
每一個神經細胞只表達某種特定的
protein out
蛋白質出來
The same gene can express different proteins
同一個基因可它表達蛋白質不一樣
Then this is like its ID card
那這個就好像它的身分證一樣
That is to say
也就是說
I just want to express this
我就是要表達這個
express one of the proteins
表達其中一種蛋白質
from a class of proteins like this
從某一類蛋白質這樣子
Then these proteins will go to
那這些蛋白質會跑到
speed surface up
速度的表面上去
So when it's two speeds
所以當它兩根速度
when we touch each other
要碰在一起的時候
then see
那就看到
This protein is the same
這個蛋白質是同一個
so what do we do
所以我們就怎麼樣
hold on to each other
就互持開來了
It's a very simple truth
這是很簡單的一個道理
That is to say we give
也就是說我們給
One identity card per nerve cell
每一個神經細胞一個身分證
Its two dendrites have to touch together
它的兩根樹突要碰在一起
they can check
它們就可以對一下
we are the same
我們是同一個身份
Then we avoid it like this
那我們就避開來這樣子
So the dendrites of this same neuron
所以這個同一個神經細胞的樹突
must avoid
必須要自我迴避
This is an interesting example
這是一個有趣的例子
The other thing to avoid is actually
那另外一種要迴避的其實也是
quite special that is to say
蠻特別的就是說
we just saw that
我們剛剛看到那個
The same goes for the nerve cells on the retina
視網膜上面的神經細胞也是一樣
Each cell occupies a space like this
每一個細胞都要佔領一個空間這樣子
So we can see that
所以我們就可以看到說
this dendrite
這個樹突
from different cells
不同細胞來的
the same nerve cell
同一種神經細胞
different dendrites
不同的樹突
This is the red cell body here
這個是紅色的細胞本體在這裡
This is a green cell body
這是一個綠色的細胞本體
their dendrites grow
它們的樹突就長過來
just grow up, right?
就長過來對不對
they'll get very, very close to each other
它們彼此會走得非常非常近
what we just said
那我們剛剛講過
It's going to cover its entire body with dendrites
它要把整個全身都佈滿樹突
So they should be as full as possible
所以它們要盡量佈滿
But they don't want to be intertwined
可是它們又不想交錯在一起
so you see some details
所以你看到一些細節
For example, the red and green
譬如說這個紅色跟綠色
almost all close
幾乎都接得很近
but not together
可是就不碰在一起
do not touch together
不碰在一起
They're going to keep building a field
他們要繼續建立一個領域
The field is bigger the better
這個領域是越大越好
we can get very close
大家能夠非常接近
but got very very close
但是到了非常非常接近
They avoid it when approached
要靠近的時候他們就會迴避一下
It's just that I don't want to occupy your space
就是我不去佔領你的空間
you don't come to occupy my space
你不來佔領我的空間
Here is a very simple experiment
這裡有一個很簡單的實驗
to explain this matter
來說明這個事情
In fact, what we just said is very simple.
其實也是我們剛剛講的很簡單
you use a laser
你用一個雷射
kill this cell
把這個細胞殺死
Of course those speeds are gone.
那這些速度當然就不見了
so it's easy
所以就很簡單
everyone knows the answer
大家都知道答案
just grow up
就是會長過來
Come over and help him cover
長過來幫他cover一下
this has an area
這個有一個區域
so just cover it
所以就把它cover過去
So this is a very simple example
所以這個是一個很簡單的例子
they will build their own domain
他們會建立自己的領域
But they can't exchange each other
可是他們又互不清換
So in this body section
所以這個一個體節裡面
There are actually only three of these neurons
其實只有三顆這種神經細胞
Three blue, green, yellow
三顆的藍色、綠色、黃色
build your own domain
建立自己的領域
not interchangeable
又互不清換
another said
另外一個說的
speed self avoidance
速度自我迴避
Then let's look at this example
然後我們再來看這一個例子
In fact, everyone, take a look at this moving
這其實大家看一下這個moving
watch the color change
看顏色的變化
did you see
有沒有看到
Which color is the tree diagram we are talking about
那哪一個顏色是我們講的樹圖
green, right?
綠色嘛 對不對
So we just talked about a psycho
所以我們剛剛講一個神經病
Then when you look at the red, there are grids of cells, are there any?
那大家看紅色的時候是一格一格的細胞有沒有
That's epidermal cells
那這是表皮細胞
Those tree diagrams actually grow under the epidermal cells
那這些樹圖事實上是長在表皮細胞的下面
It has a very tight bond with epidermal cells
它跟表皮細胞有非常緊密的一個結合
Underneath this epidermal cell is this
在這個表皮細胞下面有這個
one layer of this
一層這個
The tree map just grows under this skin
樹圖就剛好長在這個表皮下面
So outside stimuli
所以外面的外界的刺激
These tree diagrams can feel
這些樹圖就可以感覺到
Then send the signal over like this
然後就把訊號傳過去這樣子
so
所以
like we actually have researched a little bit of this stuff
像我們實際上是有研究一點點這個東西
we found out that
我們就發現說
Eh
欸
This is an epidermal cell
這是一個表皮細胞
it's a glove like this
它是一個隔壯這樣子
one by one like this
一個一個這樣子
it is tree map red
它是樹圖紅色的
It grows under the epidermis like this
它就長在這個表皮細胞的下面這樣子
may see say
可能會看到說
Below this tree diagram
這個樹圖下面
There are also some green proteins
也有一些綠色的蛋白質
It's the same protein as this epidermal cell protein
跟這個表皮細胞蛋白質是一樣的蛋白質
So actually this epidermal cell is here
所以其實這個表皮細胞在這邊
is helping the tree graph grow
是在幫助樹圖的生長
assisting its growth
在輔助它的生長
so that it can be stabilized on this epidermal cell
讓它可以穩定在這個表皮細胞上面
it grows
它長過去
Epidermal cells may have some protein secretion
表皮細胞可能就有一些蛋白質分泌
stick it on top
把它緊貼在上面
let it stabilize
讓它能夠穩定下來
Then we just talked about what the tree diagram has
那我們剛剛講說樹圖有什麼
There are extended and retracted, right?
有伸出去有縮回來對不對
if it is so stable
它這樣穩定的話
The tree diagram is less likely to shrink back
樹圖就比較不會縮回來
it grows at a constant distance like this
它就可以穩定的距離生長這樣子
Those are epidermal cells
那可是表皮細胞
of course we know this
我們當然知道這個
not entirely good
也不是完全是好人
It also sometimes plays this
它有時候也是扮演這個
double face role
雙面人的角色
What we just saw was an epidermal cell
我們剛剛看到是一個表皮細胞
A pair of tree diagrams
對樹圖的一個
growing a stable one
生長的一個穩定的一個
support
支持
So here is the same group of epidermal cells
那這裡是同樣一群表皮細胞
But they are actually eating the tree diagram
可是他們確實是在吞這個樹圖
You see this tree diagram
你看到這個樹圖
This treemap is dying
這樹圖已經快要滅亡了
you see the whole and disappear
你看到整個就不見了
In this movie that was shot for about half an hour
在這個大概半個小時的拍的這個movie裡面
You're swallowed when you see a tree diagram
你看到樹圖就被吞掉
You see that this tree diagram is cut off more specifically
你看到這一個樹圖的切斷更特別
You see a little bit of the tail being pulled away like this
你看到尾巴一小段就這樣子被拉扯開來
Pull it off and it disappears like this
拉扯掉就不見了這樣子
So this epidermal cell also
所以這個表皮細胞也
This is really double-faced
這個真的是像雙面人
He supported the growth of this tree map in the early days
他早期的時候在支持這個樹圖的生長
Gobble up the treemap at a later stage
到晚期的時候就吞噬這個樹圖
It's an interesting experiment
這是一個很有趣的一個實驗
I appreciate it every time I watch a movie
我每次看電影的時候我都非常欣賞
how to swallow this
這個怎麼吞掉
This tree diagram this neuron is here
這個樹圖這個神經細胞在這裡
Ontology is here
本體在這裡
It's very complicated with several strands
它這好幾根很複雜
Its tree diagram is going to grow
它的樹圖要長出來
to fill the space like this
要把空間填滿這樣子
we can see say this tree stand
我們可以看到說這個樹架
look at this purple one
看這一根紫色的
it's green
它這個綠色的
this black like this
這個黑色這樣子
And then they went to shoot this inside
然後他們去拍裡面的這個
signal before being swallowed
要被吞掉之前的訊號
If you look at the picture on the right
那大家如果看右邊這張圖
did you see
有沒有看到
This looks like this lightning
這個很像這個閃電
Suddenly one lighted up, right?
突然就有一根亮起來對不對
The first root is here, the second root is there
第一根在這裡 第二根在那裡
Then we look at this diagram that means
那我們看這個示意圖就是說
It's not a schematic, it's just
不是示意圖就是說
an image of that single time
把那個單時間的一個影像
then this one
然後這一根
this one
就是這一根
suddenly light up together
突然一起亮起來
Then this one will be swallowed
那這一根就被吞掉
next time this
下一個時間點這個
all lit up
整個亮起來
Then this one will be swallowed
那這一根就被吞掉
that seems to mean
那似乎就是說
This diagram is not
這個術圖並不是
all together all together like this
大家一起全部一起這樣子
In fact there is a
而事實上是有一個
have a sense of order
有一個順序的感覺
That is to say, one of them is swallowed whole.
就是說要嘛就是一根全部被吞掉
Then the others are later
那其他還比較晚的時候
just got swallowed like this
才被吞掉這樣子
there seems to be a signal
那似乎有個訊號
must accumulate to a certain
必須要累積到某一個
Above critical point
臨界點以上
Then this root diagram will be swallowed like this
然後這一根術圖就會被吞掉這樣子
This is actually a bit like some
這個其實有點像一些
Let's look at one of the neurotransmitter disorders
我們看一個神經推發性疾病的一個
diagram, this is a
術圖,這是一個
a cerebellar spinal atrophy
小腦脊髓萎縮症的一個
a certain kind, this first kind
一個某一類的,這個第一類的
cerebellar spinal atrophy
這個小腦脊髓萎縮症
Then you saw this one
那你看到說這一個
Pokinji Cell
Pokinji Cell
This art picture originally looked very dense
這個術圖本來長得非常的貌密
Like this, there are several like this
這樣子,有好幾根這樣子
It should be said that when the disease occurs
應該說這個疾病發生的時候
Sometimes it's like one of them is missing
有時候是其中一根不見的這樣子
one missing like this
一根不見的這樣子
The rest of the place looks pretty good.
那其他地方看起來長得還不錯這樣子
not bad
還不錯
So this seems to respond
所以這個似乎可以反應
This can be done as a pattern
這個可以做一個模式
study some diseases
再研究一些疾病上
In fact, we often say
那其實我們常常說
During development these articulations
在發育的時候這些術圖
It has a lot to do with our nerve cells
跟我們的神經細胞很大關係
That seems to grow as much as possible
那似乎要長得越多越好
The more secretive the better
越貌密越好
In fact, our development is often not like this
那其實我們發育常常不是這樣子
We started by talking about our
我們一開始講說我們的
Like cells, we do enough
像細胞一樣,我們要做了夠多
Then in some places how to
然後在某一些地方要把怎麼樣
let this cell die
要讓這一細胞死掉
and then be able to construct
然後才能夠建構
something pretty with a stretched eye
一些漂亮的一個裹延的眼睛
The picture is the same
那術圖也是一樣
We have a nice model here
我們在這裏面有一個很好的模型
After the dendrite grows
這個樹突長出來以後
at some point it has to be broken
在某個時候它就必須要被斷掉
Then keep the cell body
那這細胞本體來留著
Axons also remain
軸突也留著
That's only if the dendrites are all broken.
那只有這個樹突全部碎掉這樣子
What about after it's broken?
那碎掉以後呢
This nerve cell can then grow a new tree protrusion
這個神經細胞就可以再長出新的樹突出來
Execute the new function like this
執行新的功能這樣子
So this dendrite actually has a modification during development
所以這個樹突其實在發育過程中有一個修飾
or the process of shrinking
或者萎縮的這個過程
fix it like this
把它修飾掉這樣子
Well, this is actually in human development
那這個其實在人的發育
In fact, this phenomenon is also very clear
其實這個現象也是非常的清楚
is what we know to say
就是我們知道說
newborn baby
剛出生的這個嬰幼兒
It is between 0 and 2 years old
它在0歲到2歲的時候
we look at this line
我們看這條線
this normal this line
這條正常的這個線
it actually keeps increasing
它事實上還是持續增加
The dendrites will keep increasing, right?
這個樹突會一直增加增加對不對
It will increase to 0 when it is about 2 years old
大概增加到2歲的時候到達0點
But then the dendrites start to decrease
但是再過來就是樹突開始會減少
At first it will be reduced to a normal number like this
開始會減少到一個正常的一個數字這樣子
Then this may mean doing a little more at the beginning
那這個可能就是說一開始做多一點
Then let the neurons form different grades
然後讓神經細胞形成不同的年級
If it's too much then fix it up
到時候太多的話就把它修飾掉
it's a simple idea
這是一個簡單的想法
Then we found that the scientist
那我們發現這個科學家
We found this diagram that says this modification
我們發現說這個修飾的這個術圖
It's actually very important not to grow too much
其實很重要 不能長得太多
For example, when you are autistic
那譬如說在自閉症的時候
Some of
的一些
Children will find that his art diagram begins
兒童中就會發現說他的術圖一開始
is more long
是長得比較多的
then too much
然後過多
Then he will have the modified
然後他會有雖然有修飾
But it has not been modified to a normal phenomenon like this
可是並沒有修飾到一個正常的現象這樣子
that in certain other developments like this
那在某些其他的發育譬如說像這個
traditionally called schizophrenia
傳統上叫精神分裂
It is now called Sijue Sitiao
那現在改稱叫思覺思條
this red line
這一條紅色的線
you can see say
你可以看到說
when he was growing
他發育的時候是
It is normal to increase
增加的時候是正常
at the top
到最高點的時候
He came down with too much grooming
他下來的時候上是修飾過多了
too much retouching
修飾過多
so
所以說
This may be a possibility that caused his thoughts.
這可能就是造成他這個思覺思條的一個可能性
If you are mentally handicapped, that means
那智能障礙的話就是說
It may not be long enough at the beginning
可能一開始長的數目就不夠多
Then it will be too much to fix it like this
然後修飾下來會修太多了這樣子
So he is also better than the normal picture
所以他也比正常的這個術圖
also slightly
也是稍微
So this is our epiphysis during development
所以這個是在發育過程中我們的宿突
There is a process of adding and modifying
有一個增加跟修飾的過程
We want to say that additions and modifications are normal numbers
我們希望說增加跟修飾是正常的數字
not only in development
不只在發育
some geriatric diseases
一些老年疾病
don't talk about geriatric diseases
不要講老年疾病
later neurological diseases
後來的一些神經性的疾病
Alzheimer's disease
例如說阿茲海默症
Said that the increase in speed is more than
說速突的增加就比
This is the body and speed of a normal nerve cell
這是一個正常的神經細胞的本體跟它的速度
We're seeing Alzheimer's brain degeneration
我們看到阿茲海默症大腦退化
The speed of nerve cells is reduced very much
神經細胞的速度減少非常多
under stress or anxiety
在壓力或者是焦慮
under strong pressure
強大的壓力之下
Its speed will actually decrease accordingly.
它的速度其實也會跟著減少
So this provides us with say
所以這個提供了我們說
We want to study the relationship between speed and these diseases
我們要研究速度跟這些疾病的關係
We have a body in our laboratory
我們實驗室有用一個體材
Studying this Fear of Spiritual Policing
研究這個怕精神施政
This is mainly a doctor coming to our laboratory
這個主要是一個醫師到我們實驗室來
Very special. He hopes to use Guoying as a model to study the life cycle of Phra Chiang.
很特別 他希望用果營來當模式來研究這個帕清生時程
It turned out to be very interesting, so I'll take a moment to report back
結果變得非常有趣 所以我這邊跟大家利用一點時間報告一下
Well, Pa Qingsheng is actually not a doctor, so this may not be very accurate.
那這個帕清生其實我不是醫生 所以這個講得不一定會很準
But Pa Qingsheng at least we know that there are a few characteristics
不過帕清生至少我們知道說有幾個特徵
That means fighting and slowing down when prohibited
就是說禁止的時候會戰斗 運動遲緩
Very stiff limbs and heel area Very unstable posture
四肢跟區幹非常僵硬 姿勢非常不穩定
Those who are interested can go online to watch some videos, which is actually very clear
這個有興趣的人可以上網去看一些影片其實是非常清楚
So what I want to say is that in fact, about two thousand years later
那我要講的就是說其實在後來大概兩千年以後
During Phra Ching's birth, he found that many words caused
帕清生時程發現說很多的引起
This is partly due to genetic mutations
有一部分的原因是因為基因發生突變
Of course, there is another part that everyone thinks is related to the environment.
那當然有另外一部分大家認為是環境的關係
But there are different theories. Some people think it's mostly genetic.
可是這有不同的理論 有些人覺得說應該大部分是基因的問題
That's because the environmental factor is the most important factor
那因為環境的因素最重要的因素
it's a matter of age
就是一個年齡的問題
This happens when older
當年齡越大的時候發生這個
Pagene's chances are higher
帕基因的機率就越高
that sometimes you just because you have the gene
那有時候你只是因為你有這個基因
you do not know
你不知道
It's just that people may die from various other factors
只是可能人對死於可能其他各種因素
Cancer, this, or injury, or something
癌症啦這個這個或傷高啦或什麼的
so
所以
so you just didn't
所以你只是沒有
Didn't live long enough to say let your pagene happen
沒有活到說讓你的帕基因發生
But that said you might have this
但是就是說你可能有這個
genetic mutation in
基因的突變在裡面
That
那
He will find that there are many genes in people
他會發現說人裡面發現很多基因
this
這個
They use this PRK Park the most
他們最用這個PRK Park
This one is named 12345678 to District 18
這個來命名的12345678到18區
That's their normal
那這是他們的一般的
The name of this gene that everyone is calling
大家在叫的這個基因的名字
Then
然後
their protein or something
他們的蛋白質什麼的
That
那
I won't talk about it one by one
我這不一一講
But here it is found that
不過這裡面發現說
many genes
很多的基因
in the state camp
在國營裡面都有
Probably at least 60-70% of all genes
大概至少六七成的所有的基因
that's weird
那這個就很奇怪
The state camp only lives for 60 days
國營才活六十天
that person lives at least
那人至少活
It takes sixty years for a person to get this
人要六十年以後才會得這個
Over 60 years old
六十歲以上
over sixty-five years old
六十五歲以上
The gene born of that Depak
那個得帕基因生的基因
become so tall
變很高這樣子
So why does this gene exist in the state-run
所以說為什麼這個基因在國營裡面會有
In fact, the explanation is quite simple.
其實這個解釋也蠻簡單就是說
how about a lot of genes
很多的基因怎麼樣
Actually it has its normal function
其實它有它的正常功能
It's just because the function of this gene has changed after the mutation
只是因為突變以後這個基因功能變了
Then maybe something builds up in the body
然後可能有一些東西累積在身體裡面
when you get old
當你到老的時候
It starts producing a change like this
它就開始產生一個變化這樣子
Of course, the reason is still hard to say
當然那個原因還是很難講
But what I want to tell you today is
不過我今天要跟大家講的是
One of these genes is called LORK2
其中一個基因叫LORK2
It also has this gene in the state run
它在國營裡面也有這個基因
This gene is actually
這個基因其實是
Most commonly found in Parkinson's municipalities
帕金森市政府裡面最常發現
a gene with a mutation
有突變的一個基因
Call it Pog8 or call it LORK2
叫Pog8或叫LORK2
We all have to be called LORK in the state.
國營我們都要叫LORK這樣子
it has a protein
它有一個蛋白質
There are many functional regions on the protein, like this
蛋白質上面有非常多有功能的區域這樣子
several areas
好幾個區域
everyone can see
大家可以看得到
Then there are many different places on it
那它上面有非常多不同地方
can mutate
可以發生突變
We know that our chromosomes come in pairs
我們知道我們的染色體都是成雙成對的
But as long as you have one of the chromosomes
但只要你其中有一個染色體的
A gene on LRK2
LRK2上的一個基因
If a mutation occurs
發生突變的話
Then you add this
那這個你就增加這個
The chances of getting Parkinson's become very, very high.
得帕金森森的機率就變得非常非常高這樣子
There is one of the most famous mutation points
那其中有一個最有名的一個突變點
called G2019S
叫做G2019S
Everyone can remember this
這個大家可以記一下
Call G2019S
叫G2019S
This is the most commonly found mutation
這個是最常被找到的一個突變
Then its this feature
然後它的這個特徵
The characteristics of this mutation
這個突變的特徵
It's a very typical Parkinson's
是非常典型的一個帕金森森
Then he made the protein very active
然後他讓這個蛋白質的活性變得非常強
Then they found out that in some of the Jews
然後他們發現說在一些猶太人裡面
Or some North African Jewish arts
或者是一些北非的一些猶太藝有裡面
The chances are very, very high
這個機率非常非常高
The probability of this G2019S happening is very high
這個G2019S發生的機率非常高
Then if you go to Google
那大家如果去Google一下
you can find this person
就可以發現這個人
this very important person
這個非常重要的人
very important to the world
對世界有非常重要的
A person with a major impact, he also got this G2019S mutant
重大影響的人 他也得了這個G2019S的突變種
a co-founder of Google
就是一個Google的一個共同創辦人
Say Brin
Sage Brin
his story is interesting
他這個故事很有趣
He was around 2006
他在大概2006年吧
he discovered early
他早期有發現
Discovered around 2000
大概2000年左右發現
His mom has Parkinson's
他媽媽得了帕金森時辰
Then he always felt that it was the influence of the environment
然後他一直覺得那個是環境的影響
It's not genetics, it's environmental influences
不是基因的 是環境的影響
He felt that people with Parkinson's also understood environmental factors at that time
他就覺得那時候對帕金森人也了解環境的因素
and then at 20...because he makes a lot of money
然後在20...因為他賺很多錢
Got Google right?
弄了Google對不對
He imagined that the money was a lot
他想像這個錢很多
he took a wife
他取了一個太太
This lady is a student of biology
這個太太就是學生物的
in our field
是我們這個領域的
Then he pays his wife
然後他就支出他太太
to start a company
去創辦了一個公司
Some people should have heard of this company called 23andMe
這公司有些人應該聽過叫23andMe
the sequence that can sequence your DNA
就是可以定序你的DNA的序列
sequence the DNA
定序這個DNA的序列
He gave his wife money and started a company like this
他給他太太錢 然後去開的公司這樣子
Maybe it was a girl back then...
那時候可能還是女...
Then he also said to sequence your DNA
那他也就說那要把你的DNA定序一下
he said yes
他說好啊
He sequenced his DNA
他就把他DNA定序
After the sequence is finished, let's see if we want to take a look
定序完以後說我們要不要來看看
Is there any mutation?
有沒有什麼突變啊
He said okay come and see
他說好啊來看就來看
Let's say you really have the G2019S mutation
來看說你真的有G2019S的突變
This is really a bit of this exciting
這個真的是有一點這個令人
But I think you can go to that blog to see this
不過我覺得這個大家可以上那個部落格去看
he speaks very well
他講得非常好
He said that he actually thinks he is luckier than everyone else.
他就說其實他覺得他比大家幸運
Because he thinks that when people get old
因為他覺得人老了以後
always die of a disease
總是會死於某一種疾病
don't know what disease
不知道什麼疾病
It's not cancer, it's Alzheimer's disease
不是癌症啊就是什麼阿茲海默症
Then he was lucky at such a young age
那他有幸在這麼年輕的時候
in your 30s
30多歲的時候
You can know what diseases you will get when you get old
可以知道自己老了以後會得什麼病
so he can start now
所以他現在可以開始去
Prevention of Parkinson's as a whole
預防整個帕金森之稱
let him happen later
讓他晚一點發生
or reduce the chances of him happening
或減少他發生的機率
or how like this
或怎麼樣這樣子
That's just the mutation of G2019S
那不過這G2019S的這個突變
actually full
其實是滿
pretty bad mutation
蠻糟糕的一個突變
The probability of being called Parkinson's is very high
大概會得帕金森之稱的機率非常高
very high
非常高
So for him it is
所以對他來講是
A lot of the money he earned has been used to do research on fear of mental evidence
已經把他賺的錢非常多拿去做怕精神事證的研究
study like this
研究這樣子
Our laboratory also did a little bit of the effect of the G2019S mutation on the rapid burst
我們實驗室也做了一點點G2019S突變對於速突的影響
You can see that this is the growth of a normal nerve cell
你可以看到這個是一個正常的神經細胞的長出來的速突
very healthy very good
非常健康 非常好
However, if the G2019S mutation is expressed
可是如果表達了G2019S突變的時候
Sutu grows sparser than the Sutu here
速突長得就比這邊的速突要稀疏
much less, much shorter
要少多了 短多少多
Then it's pretty sparse
然後蠻稀疏的這樣子
So it's a pretty bad mutation
所以這是一個蠻不好的突變
In human beings, fear of mental evidence will actually lead to a decrease in excess
那在人類怕精神事證其實會引起多八岸糞蜜的減少
This dohagan is a neurotransmitter
這個多八岸是一個神經傳導物質
Then in our highlight from bad to bad
然後在我們的突出裡面從一個一個糟糕
Then Feimi this multi-octagan
然後蜚蜜這個多八岸
Send this speed and receive it to the next nerve cell like this
送給這個速度接受到傳到下一個神經細胞這樣子
Then the second is to say
然後第二個就是說
This neuron that secretes this dopamine
這個分泌這個多巴胺的神經元
Nerve cells also become very few
神經細胞也會變得非常少
from this normal to this
從這個正常的到這個
This one has Parkinston's this black
這個有帕金斯頓斯頓的這個黑色
This one representing this dopamine neuron is gone.
這個代表這個多巴胺神經元的就不見了
gone
不見了
Then we can also see this experiment in Chinese
那這個實驗我們在國文也可以看得到
Did you see that we are in Chinese
你看到說我們在國文裡面
Then we can dye these many dopamine nerves
然後這些很多的多巴胺神經我們可以染得到
Then if express G2019S
然後如果表達G2019S的話
This neuron also decreases
這種神經元也就跟著減少
And it is decreasing with time
而且是隨著時間在跟著減少
decrease over time
隨著時間跟著減少
just like people
那就跟人一樣
Then there are problems with these sure movements
然後這些果然的運動也有問題
worse
比較糟糕一點
Then
然後
so
所以說
In fact, it can be used to imitate this
其實果然可以用來模仿這個
A model of such a study by Parkinston
帕金斯頓斯頓的這種一個研究的一個模型
that here
那這裡
This is Dr. Lin in our laboratory
這個我們實驗室那個林醫師
He did a very interesting experiment
他就做了一個很有趣的實驗
he just said ok then
他就說 OK 那
It is said that this speed can be used as a model to study the Parkinson's reproductive disease of G2019S
說把這個速度可以來當作模型來研究G2019S的帕金生殖症的話
Then is there any antidote that can be found?
那到底有沒有什麼解藥可以做 可以找喔
Then we know the US FDA US Food and Drug Administration
那我們知道美國FDA 美國食物藥物的管理局喔
They've probably approved maybe a thousand drugs so far.
他們大概至今為止核准了大概上千個藥物喔
This drug can treat various diseases in the human body
可以在人體上治療各種病的這個藥物喔
Then these drugs are probably harmless to the body.
那這些藥物大概就是所對身體無害
There is a little cure for a certain disease, there are some more or less curative functions like this
對某一種疾病有一點點治療 有一些或多或少治療的功能這樣子
Since these drugs are harmless to the human body, he asked
那既然這些藥物對人體無害 他就問說
Do these drugs have any effect on Parkinson's reproductive disease caused by G2019S?
那這些藥物有沒有什麼對G2019S引起的帕金生殖症
Has a positive protective or positive lifting or healing effect
有一個正面的保護 或者是正面的提升或治療的效果
Then this experiment is unlikely to be done in humans or mice
那這個實驗不太可能在人或老鼠生這樣做喔
For this person, you need about a thousand kinds of medicines, how many people will it take to test it out, right?
這個人的話你大概要一千種藥 那要多少人才能夠試驗得出來 對不對
the mouse even if the mouse does
那老鼠 即使老鼠做
also very very expensive
也非常非常貴
Rats just have to do one drug experiment
老鼠只要做一個藥物的實驗
maybe a lot of money
可能就是一個蠻多的錢
But in Drosophila
可是在果蠅做的話
very simple
很簡單
a laboratory
一個實驗室
a summer vacation
一個暑假
An experiment that can probably be done
大概就可以做得完的實驗
so
所以說
we'll do it with fruit flies
我們就用果蠅來做
cheap and fast
又便宜又快
So he took this fruit fly
所以他就把這個果蠅
look at its speed
看它的速度的樣子
this normal
這個正常的
Then this is the expression of G2019S
那這是表達G2019S的
That's in the 1000 drugs
那在這個1000個藥物裡面
just found out say 1 2 3 4
就發現說1 2 3 4
There are 4 medicines in total
總共有4個藥
And let the speed go back up again
還讓這個速度又漲回去了
speed up again
速度又漲回去
You saw that the speed increase is not bad
你看到說這個速度漲還不錯
that seems to shadow
那似乎影
Talk about not doing well for G2019S
講說搞不好對G2019S
The cause of the boogie is that there is a
引起的趴金是有一個
The role of compensation
節償的作用
or one is one
或者一個是一個
Then he took one of the medicines
那他對其中一個藥
This Lobar Stating
這個Lobar Stating
do one more research
又做更多的一個研究
Drosophila
發現說它在果蠅
I had a problem with exercise
本來運動有問題
It can also make it run a bit better
它也可以讓它跑得好一點
and then make it
然後讓它變得
The ability to exercise becomes stronger, like this
運動的能力變強一點這樣子
many people may know
那很多人可能知道
What is Lobar Stating?
Lobar Stating是什麼藥
right
對不對
Stating this medicine
Stating的這個藥
this this steroids
這個這個擋固醇
this antilipidemic
這個抗血脂
then let you this
然後讓你這個
Then
然後
Its paper was published in 2016
它的這個論文在2016年的發表
Probably published at the beginning of the year like this
大概是年初發表這樣子
Then at the end of 2015
那在2015年的這個年底
There is a clinical trial in the UK
英國的有一個臨床的試驗的
They used a similar one of a Stating
他們就用了一個Stating的一個類似的一個
The drug is called Symbostating
藥物叫Symbostating
It is a relatively able to penetrate this
它這是一個比較能夠穿透這個
This drug for the brain-blood barrier
腦血屏障的這個藥
it can
它可以
because this treats this
因為這個治療這個
Cholesterol probably doesn't need to get into the brain
膽固醇大概不需要進到大腦
But this Symbostating can enter the brain more easily
可是這個Symbostating可以比較容易進入大腦
They just experimented and said we're going to try this medicine
他們就試驗說我們要拿這個藥來試試看
Does it have a protective effect on Parkinson's life?
是不是對帕金森生生有一個保護的效果
that this is not to say
那這個不是要說
that is
就是說
Well, sure enough research seems to
欸 在果然的研究似乎
actually quite effective
事實上是蠻有效的
And these medicines are safe medicines
而且這些藥都是安全的藥
so you say
所以你說欸
Can this be used directly for human experiments?
這個是不是就可以直接拿來做人體上的試驗
So what I'm going to say is
那我要講的就是說
Hey this
欸 這個
Seems like a nice tool indeed
果然似乎是一個不錯的工具
can be used to make a very simple
可以拿來做一個非常簡單
A process of early drug screening
初期的一個藥物篩選的一個過程
that seems to work
那似乎可以
Maybe after the whole five years, there should be two or three years left
或許整個五年後,應該剩下兩三年了
Let's see how they fare
我們來看看他們這個效果怎麼樣
Then use this research, then use it to do research is actually very special
那用這個研究,那用果然作研究其實很特別
In fact, no one believes that our algal medicines can have any effect on Parkinson's
其實沒有人相信說我們這些藻藥可以對帕金森有什麼效果
But for the sheer joy of research, quite a few students want to experiment like this
不過就純就研究的樂趣而言,蠻多學生就想要這樣來試驗
Another student, he is in a department of food nutrition
另外有一個學生,他在一個食品營養的一個科系
He said that their laboratory is dedicated to studying the protective effect of Tianma on human nerves.
他就說他們實驗室專門在研究天馬的對人的神經的保護作用
They want to see fruit camps, Parkinson's-style fruit camps
他們想看看用果營,帕金森式的果營
See if there is a protective effect
看是不是有一個保護作用
Traditionally we know traditional Chinese medicine
傳統上我們知道傳統的中藥
In fact, this is what people have used for thousands of years, and it is harmless to the human body.
那其實這個是幾千年來大家用過的這個對人體是無害
And it has some protective effect
而且是有些保護的效果
It's just how to protect it
只是說它怎麼保護啦
or to protect some kind of disease
或保護什麼的病啦
Now medical progress should be defined more clearly
那現在應該醫學進步定義得比較清楚
Then can we repeat some experiments to see
那我們是不是可以重複一些實驗來看看
is this pegasus
這個天馬是不是
have this effect
有這個效果
In fact, the tradition used to be a lot like
那其實傳統以前很多像
hypocrites
hypocrites
he said early on
他早期就說
He also said that the food
他也說過就是讓食物呢
is your medicine
是你的藥
let medicine be your food
那讓藥是你的食物
That's actually what we call the homology of the history of medicine in Chinese.
那其實就是我們中文講的藥史同源這樣子
Then you have heard many stories about Li Qingyun
那這個大家聽過很多李清雲的故事
I don't know if that is true or not
那個是真是假還不知道
But you can Google it
不過大家Google一下就知道
Claimed to be born in the Qianlong period of the Qing Dynasty
號稱是清朝乾隆時期出生
that lived until the Republic of China
那一直活到民國
This one person in 20 years
20幾年的這個一個人
Also reported in the New York Times
這個New York Times上也有報導
Also reported on the Washington Post
Washington Post上也有報導
But to be honest, no one
可是到底是真來講的其實沒有人
can fully prove it
可以完全證明啦
However, when he was interviewed
不過他當初接受訪問的時候
When interviewed during the Republic of China, he said
在民國時期接受訪問的時候就說
He uses Chinese medicine as his
他就是以中藥當他的這個
this food looks like this
這個食物這樣子
A concept of homology in the history of medicine looks like this
一個藥史同源的一個概念這樣子
So let's take a look
那所以我們就拿來看一下
this right
這個對
Does Tianma have any protective effect on Parkinson's?
天馬對帕金森斯這種有沒有什麼保護的作用
Well, it's very clear for everyone to see this.
那其實大家跟我看這個就很清楚
This experiment is actually very simple
這個實驗其實非常簡單
Then we also found some high school students to do the experiment
那我們也找了一些高中生就可以來做實驗
You'll see it says this is a control group experiment
你會看到說這個是控制組的實驗
This is what G2019S just said
這個是G2019S剛剛講過的
Then what we want is that the fruit fly can climb over this 8 cm line
那我們要的是這個果蠅能夠爬過這個8公分的這個線
So we knock the flies down to the very bottom
所以我們把果蠅敲到最底部
See how many fruit flies can climb 8 cm in one time
在一個時間內看有多少隻果蠅可以爬過8公分
Let's just videotape and see how many go by
我們就錄影看看有多少隻過去
Then you can see that when the G2019S mutation is said
那你可以看到說這個G2019S突變的時候
Lots of fruit flies just stay down there
很多果蠅就停留在下面
It doesn't pass too much, and it doesn't move too much.
它就不太過去了爬不太動了
Only two or three have climbed here
爬到這裡大概只有兩隻三隻過去
only three passed
就只有三隻過去
Most of the others are below
其他大部分都是下面
Can't go up
上不去
There are quite a few more in the control group
控制組還有蠻多隻過去
So we fed it different doses of this pegasus in the fruit fly
那我們在果蠅內就給它餵不同劑量的這個天馬
0.1% 0.5% 1.0% of the time
0.1% 0.5% 1.0%的時候
you see say
你就看到說
This same G2019
這個同樣的G2019
Some really started to climb well.
有些果然就開始爬得不錯了
Climbing well is more than 8 cm line
爬得不錯就超過8公分的線
Then we can see that the statistics here also say the same.
那我們可以看到這邊的統計也是這樣講
To pegasus when we can see say
為了天馬的時候我們可以看到說
It actually has an effect
它的效果其實是有的
Can make it climb over 8 cm
可以讓它爬過8公分的運
That is to say, to restore its athletic ability
就是說恢復它的運動能力
Then let's look at the growth of speed
那我們去看速度的生長
The speed of growth has also returned to this way
速度的生長也有回去這樣子
this is an experiment
這個是一個實驗
And it is really Parchment
而且用的是果然的Parchment
So there is nothing to tell you here
所以這裡沒有要跟大家講什麼
But don't try too casually.
不過大家也不要太隨便去試
However, traditional Chinese medicine of Tianma
不過天馬傳統的中藥
It manufactures that it is essential for the blood circulation of the brain
它製造說它對於大腦的血液循環
or everything is very good
或什麼都非常好
The memory is very good like this
記憶力都非常好這樣子
then we just want to say to study
那我們只是想說來研究
Because there are some chemical components in Tianma
因為天馬裡面有一些化學成分
The most important thing is a component called Gastroding
最主要是一個叫Gastroding成分
Then we want to say look at these chemical molecules
那我們想說看這些化學分子
Or because traditional Chinese medicine is a rich prescription
或者是因為中藥是一個富方
often several
常常有好幾種
Then we want to try to see which ones are added to which ones.
那我們想試試看哪些跟哪些加在一起
that has a better effect
那有一個比較好的效果
At the same time, we also want to see
那同時我們也想去看看說
how did it come about
它到底怎麼樣來
suppress this
抑制這個
Parkinson's called this
帕金森之稱的這個
The effect is like this
效果這樣子
at the cellular level
在細胞層次上
What the hell is it doing to the cells
它到底對細胞做了什麼事情
Then this really reminds everyone
那這個真的要提醒大家
Because we have different models in the fruit camp
因為我們在果營裡面有不同模式的
Parkinson's name
帕金森之稱
Another Parkinson's
另外一個帕金森的
another model
另外一個模型
it doesn't work at all
就一點效果都沒有
that this is very special
那這個是很特別
we feel
我們覺得說
Maybe this Pegasus is for a certain type of Parkinson's
這個天馬搞不好是對某一類的帕金森
only effective
才有效果
For some classes, it is not necessarily the effect
對某些類其實是不一定的效果
Now let's talk about precision medicine
那我們現在講精準醫學
we need to know
我們就要知道說
If you have Parkinson's
你如果得了帕金森
What kind of mutation
到底是什麼樣的突變
let you get this certificate
讓你得了這個證
then sick
然後病
Then what special
然後可以用什麼樣的特別
probably everyone
可能每一個人
The way to treat is different
要治療的方式是不一樣這樣子
So we wish to say
所以我們希望說
our research on this
我們的研究對這個
theoretically
這個學理上
Parkinson's theory
帕金森的學理上
There are some contributions like this
有一些貢獻這樣子
so i see my time is about
所以我看我的時間差不多
So finally I want to thank the lab
所以最後我要謝謝實驗室
former student
以前的學生
and postdoctoral
還有博士後
this is us
這個是我們
When we got together a few years ago, we took a big group photo like this
幾年前大家聚在一起的時候拍了一個大合照這樣子
Then this is many former students
然後這個是以前很多是以前的學生
Here's what it looks like back with a postdoctoral fellow
跟博士後的研究員回來這樣子
And now there are still many students in the laboratory
然後現在還有很多的學生在實驗室
Taken before Chinese New Year this year
今年過年前拍的
Everyone is wearing red clothes
大家穿著紅色的衣服
The Year of the Golden River Dog in Western Ocean looks like this
西洋洋的金河狗年這樣子
I won't list them all because there are too many names.
那因為太多名字我就不一一列舉
Then we have many collaborators
那我們還有很多的合作者
Like this at home and abroad
在國內跟國外這樣子
So I'm just reporting here
所以我就跟大家報告到這裡
And thank you all for listening
然後謝謝大家的聆聽
Thank you, Mr. Jane, for your wonderful speech.
謝謝我們簡老師很精采的演講
From his research using Drosophila from the basis of neurodevelopment
從他利用果蠅從基礎的神經發育的研究
to disease research
一直到疾病的研究
find drugs that might work
找到也許可能有效的藥物
let's wait
那我們等一下
Open to everyone to ask questions
開放大家現場發問
We will give a prize and a small gift to the top ten
前十位我們會送一個獎品一個小禮物
This is the 90th anniversary of the Central Plains
這個是中原九十週年
It is a coaster for our 1992 anniversary celebration this year
就是今年我們92年願慶的一個杯墊
Also before you ask
另外在大家發問之前
Let me first announce that our next month is December
我先宣布一下我們下一個月份12月份
December 25th
12月25號
Our feast of knowledge is served by our
我們的知識饗宴是由我們的
Researcher Peng Xiaoyan, Institute of Chinese Culture and Philosophy
中國文哲研究所彭曉岩研究員
he gave the lecture
他主講
assassin
刺客
Evil food
孽飲糧
This is a movie by Hou Hsiao-hsien
這個是侯孝賢的一個電影
His answer is Hou Hsiao-hsien's Tang China
他的這個複題就是侯孝賢的大唐中國
welcome everybody
歡迎大家
Come to listen to the lecture next month
下個月也照樣來聽講
then we're open right now
那我們現在現場就開放
ask questions
大家發問
then our online friends
那我們線上的朋友
You can also send us questions through that Facebook
也可以透過那個臉書提問給我們
Let's give priority to asking questions on the spot
我們先以這個現場發問為優先
please
請
sure enough larvae
果然的幼蟲
where are you
你在那個
it's not that active
它沒有那麼active
But when its foot starvation is that one
但是當它foot starvation是那一張
it is very active
它非常active
But with the G2019S on this side
可是跟這一邊這張G2019S
It is relatively inactive
它反而inactive比較相對
is there any difference
是不是有什麼差別
or something different
或者不太一樣的地方
or because it lacks food
或者是說因為它缺乏食物
but it is normal
但它是正常
But because of lack of food
可是因為缺乏食物
is to let it driving force
是讓它driving force
always looking for food
一直想要尋找食物
But it has no energy
可是它就沒有energy
so i understand
所以我太明白
Thank you
謝謝你
wow you
哇 你這個
You looked at my picture carefully.
我的圖你看得好仔細啊
I deliberately avoided talking
我故意繞開不講
still noticed by you
還是被你注意到
that just now that foot supply
那個剛剛那個foot supply
That is an experimental condition
那個是一個實驗的condition
An Experimental Situation
一個實驗的情況
Because we thought of two ways
因為我們想了兩個方法
make fruit flies crawl faster
讓果蠅爬快一點
I can never tell fruit flies
我總不能跟果蠅說
you climb faster
你爬快一點
So there are two ways
那所以有兩個方法
One is to increase the temperature a little bit
一個是把溫度提高一些些
At this time, fruit flies move
那這時候果蠅就運動
just faster
就是比較快一點
that's what we worry about
那可是我們擔心說
Results of our experiments
我們的實驗的結果
You want to say that it is because of the influence of temperature
你要說哦 是因為溫度的影響
rather than a crawling issue
而不是爬行的問題
So we have another situation
所以我們另外一個情況
That means leaving the flies without food
就是說讓果蠅沒有食物
this one with food
這個有食物的
then you think it's easy
那你想這個很簡單
There is food to move
有食物是要動
just hide in the food
就躲在食物裡就好
Started going out to find food when there was no food
沒有食物就開始出去找食物
what are you doing
幹嘛的
So the one without food really started crawling around
所以那個沒有食物的果然就開始到處爬
looking for food like this
找食物這樣子
So the case of our two different experiments
所以我們兩個不同的實驗的情況
then come
然後來
This is exactly the same as ever
這個果然又從都是一模一樣的
just the situation
只是情況
The conditions of the experiment are different
實驗的條件不一樣
See what it looks like with that prominent growth
來看看它那個突出的生長的樣子
So that's a set of experiments
所以那是一組實驗
What about this group of experiments
那這一組實驗講的
It's really all for the baby.
這個果然其實都為了寶寶的
is in the same food
就是在同在食物裡面
just have a food with pegasus
只是有一個食物有加天馬
Pegasus in a food
一個食物裡面加天馬
when we're just doing experiments
那我們只是要做實驗的時候
Just take it to the empty pipe and do it
把它拿到空管子來做而已
It used to eat the baby like this
它之前都是吃了寶寶的這樣子
good
好
ask that
請問那個
Or want to send some islands
或是想發一些什麼島嶼
That batch really
那一批果然
Those two batches really
那兩批果然
They are all LOMO
它們都是LOMO的
There is no such G2019S
沒有這種G2019S的
yes
沒錯
Thank you
謝謝你
Thanks
謝謝
Excuse me
請問一下
that generally speaking
那個一般講的是
Crabpena
抓培那種
Why does it go along the nerve
它為什麼都沿著神經走向
Is it related to the protrusion of the nerve?
是不是跟神經的突出有關
I didn't hear the first sentence
第一句我沒聽到一般的
Is there any snake skin that people talk about?
人家講的抓賠 蛇皮有嗎
snake skin is an allergy
蛇皮是一種過敏
I think it's a foam pillow
我覺得是一個泡枕
Yes, it's an immune system problem
對 這是免疫系統的問題
Does that have anything to do with the nervous system?
那跟神經系統有沒有關係
that's a good question
這是一個好問題
But our neural network
可是我們的神經網絡
in the body that nerve
在身體那個神經的那個
Zhou Tu Sutu actually looks very good
周突速突其實長得非常的
If I hadn't suddenly shown you
如果我沒有突而給大家看
In fact, the underlying dissatisfaction with this nerve
其實底下的不滿的這種神經的
This, Zhoutu and Sutu
這個這個周突跟速突
so yes
所以 對
I don't think so
我覺得可能不知道
I don't know if it's related, sorry
我不知道有沒有關係 不好意思
a hello
一個 你好
What I want to ask is that just now
我想要請問的是就是剛剛有
That's what Dr. Jane mentioned
就是簡博士有提到說
it's fast
就是速突的話
he will just follow
他會就是跟
Epidermal cells have interactions between
表皮細胞會有之間的交互關係
I'm more curious about
我比較好奇的是
When the epidermal cells eat up the tree soil one by one
表皮細胞再把樹土一根一根去把牠吃掉的時候
Where is it to make it break
牠是到底是哪邊讓牠斷掉
Is it a weaker place or where it breaks off?
是比較脆弱的地方還是牠斷掉的地方大概是怎麼樣
this is a good question
這是一個很好的問題
How to cut it off is arbitrary
到底怎麼斷掉是任意斷的
But it seems to be broken section by section
可是好像斷起來又一節一節的
The process of breaking it is actually quite special.
那它斷的過程其實是蠻特別的
that is to say every
就是說每一個
In fact, this can show a phenomenon of neurodegeneration
其實這個可以顯示到神經退化的一個現象
When the nerve degenerates, this tree soil or axis soil
神經退化的時候這個樹土或軸土
When broken, there are two forms
在斷掉的時候是有兩個形式
One we call Dying back
一個我們叫做Dying back
That is to say, it starts from the tail of the stomach and dies to the body of the cell.
就是說從胃尾巴開始往前死到這個細胞本體這樣子
section by section is broken
一節一節是斷掉
When these two places are already injured
這兩處已經在受傷的時候
After your side is broken, its tree soil or shaft soil is useless
你這邊斷掉以後它的樹土或軸土沒用
It started to die all the way to the body
它就開始一直死死死死死到本體
The other is like this, a pretty uniform one, and everyone cuts it off at the same time.
另外一種是這樣子,蠻均勻的一條,大家就同時這樣斷掉
The model I just mentioned is the second model, which means that it is actually quite uniform
我剛講的這個是第二種模型,就是說它其實蠻均勻的
start everywhere
到處都會有開始出現
the process is to say
那過程就是說
It is very special, in fact, it is a very special model, that is to say, it is close to the cell body at the beginning
它這個很特別,其實是一個很特別的模型,就是說它一開始靠近細胞本體的地方
will be cut first
會先被切一刀
How to cut this knife, in fact, is now a very important one in this field in the study of people
這個這一刀怎麼切,其實現在就是這個領域裡面在研究人非常重要的一個
The second is the knife, once it touches the body
第二就是這一刀,它一旦跟這個本體
after leaving
脫離開了以後
It starts to get empty inside, some of it
它裡面就開始會空掉,它的一些
If you're a biology student, something called microtubules will start
如果你是學生物的話,叫做microtubules會開始
break off, and then it's
斷掉,然後它的
The membrane on the surface will start to have some
表面那個membrane會開始有一些
Start with a pig, pig, pig, see what you see
先從一個豬豬豬豬,看到你看到的話
pig pig pig pig, then
豬豬豬豬,然後
At this moment
這時候
This epidermal cell will give it
這個表皮細胞再去把它給
Recycle like this, eat it up and recycle like this
回收這樣,把它吃進去回收這樣子
As for which side is recycled first and which side is later, it is actually still under study.
那整個回收哪邊先哪邊後,其實還在研究
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
The teacher just talked about this
老師剛剛有講到這個
London's taxi driver's hippocampus
倫敦的計程車司機的海馬會
i think it's very interesting
我覺得這非常有趣
the problem is
那問題是
it got bigger and smaller
它大了又變小
This process is because its cell body itself becomes larger
這過程是因為它的細胞體本身變大
or more prominent
或者是突出變多
Or the number of cells changed
還是細胞的數量改變了
then the second is
然後第二個是
When we were in college every time we hung out
我們在大學的時候每次要出去玩
That female classmate said
那個女同學都說
You have a better sense of direction
你們方向感比較好
you drive you ride
你們開車 你們騎車
I don't know if it's true or not
我不知道是真的還是假的
I don't know if there is any research
不知道有沒有研究是
Is there any difference between boys and girls?
這個男生女生在上面有沒有差別
I can't answer the second question
第二個問題我不能回答
because there are a lot of women
因為現場有很多女性
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
That
那
actually i remember
其實我記得
Grandson Mi's wife has a very good sense of direction
孫子咪的太太方向感非常好
I remember as long as
我記得好像只要
You tell her casually about a certain point in Taipei City
你跟她隨便跟她講台北市的某一個點
she can say right away
她馬上就可以說
how to go how to go
怎麼去怎麼去怎麼去
I can talk to you on the phone
電話上就可以跟你講
don't need this
不需要這個
and react immediately
而且是馬上反應的
Netizens turn to the host to turn like this
網友轉網主轉這樣子
There will be a difference between men and women
那男女性會有差別
I can't answer what I've learned
所學不經沒辦法回答
what's the first question
第一個是什麼問題
Why is it a change in nerve cells or a prominent change
為什麼到底是神經細胞的變化還是突出的變化
In fact, this question is also a very good question.
其實這個問題也是非常好的問題
Your question is on point
你這個問題是問到的點上去
it's not clear what's going on
到底是什麼回事並不清楚
Because it looks like a group of functional images
因為它這種functional image看的是一群
a large area
一個大的區域
no way to see in depth
沒辦法深入看到是
A few nerve cells are not deep enough
幾個神經細胞什麼都還不深
Not enough resolution
解析度不夠
So I kind of want to jump over and tell him to stand out
所以我是有一點想要跳過去跟他說突出
It's actually the one that built the driver in London
它其實是那個在倫敦建設司機的例子
we didn't know that
我們並不知道這樣子
I'm Lin Xiumei
我是林秀梅
I've been in radiation oncology for 20 years
我20年都在放射腫瘤科
as an administrative assistant
當行政助理
So this IC bag and poo are very interested
所以這個IC包啊 便便都很有興趣
After leaving the hospital in 1993, I did community visits
然後93年離開醫院之後就是做社區訪問
So now the election is over
那切到現在那個選舉結束嘛
That referendum, not the gender identity part
那個公投啊 不是性別認同這個部分
Because today's focus is that this gene is expressed during the mating period
因為今天的重點就是這個基因表現在配胎時期
that has already decided his fate
就是已經決定他的命運
So is this gender orientation determined at birth?
所以這個性別取向是不是也是一出生就決定了
Because while I'm doing community visits
因為雖然我在做社區訪問
I also met mommy mommy gay women
我也碰到媽媽媽咪同性的女性
Going to that foreign country to learn Buddhist scriptures and raising children
去那個國外取經 在撫養小孩
They are very serious and well prepared to do this
他們都很認真 很充分準備來做這件事
That's doing NHS long-term follow-up of teenagers
那在做國民健康署青少年的長期追蹤
There is also a little boy who wanted to be a girl since elementary school
也有一個小男生就是從國小自己就想當女生
I'm totally a long-term visit
我是完全是長期拜訪就是
Elementary school, middle school and high school to his university to serve in the army
國小國中高中到他的大學當兵服役
That's for sure he wants to be a girl
那就確定是他想當女生
So he works part-time to make money during this process
所以他這個過程中他就打工賺錢
And then by the time I'm done visiting he's actually headed south
然後到我結束拜訪他真的就去南邊
So because I'm all my own case
所以因為我都是我親身的個案
So I am very acceptable to this gender orientation
所以我對這個性別取向我是很能接受的
But why is this turbulent referendum so chaotic
可是為什麼這個紛紛擾擾的這個公投怎麼這麼混亂
Thanks
謝謝
I can't give any comments on the part of the referendum
公投的部分我不能給任何的comments
I think if it's just creatures, most of them are hermaphrodites.
我覺得如果就生物其實大部分都是兩性
You evolved to say male or female it's a
你演化過來就是說雄性或雌性這是一個
But there are many kinds of living things
但是生物是很多樣的
OK, then we also know that there are more than one or seven birds
OK那我們也知道有鳥有一七多夫的
Many creatures also have childishness, even fish can change sex
那很多生物也有童性甚至魚會變性
Even in research there's something called parthenogenesis
甚至在研究上也有所謂的孤雌生殖這種
In terms of biology, it has a lot of diversity
在生物的話就是他的多樣性是很多的
That person has been difficult for us recently, and I don't know how to say it
那人最近我們很難 我也不知道怎麼講
I also sympathize
我也很同情的
Thank you
謝謝你
The last one and the one over here
最後那一位 然後在這邊這位
Then after this one, then that one
然後在這位 先後面那位
hello professor i would like to ask
教授好 我想請問一下
Because in the past few days, it seems that there is a
因為最近幾天好像大陸那邊有一個
Gene-edited babies
基因編輯所生出來的嬰兒
Then he said that he could exempt AIDS patients
那他說宣稱說可以免除艾滯病患的
So what do you think the professor thinks about this news?
那請問一下教授對這個新聞有什麼看法呢
This thing must be wrong
這個事情一定是錯的啦
It's about things, it's not that the news is wrong
就是說事情喔 不是說新聞是錯的
something is wrong
事情是錯的
Because any experiment on humans has to go through
因為在人體上要做任何的實驗都要經過
Strictly because this is too risky
嚴格的 因為這個是太冒險
This is too risky. I think this person is for fame.
這個太冒險 這個 這個人我想是為了出名吧
Because I heard that their technology
因為我聽說他們這個技術
Chris Pratt This technique
Chris Pratt這種技術
In Hong Kong, it seems that a conference will be held in these two days
在香港好像這兩天要舉行一個大會
he was one of the speakers
他是其中一個演講者
is that ahead of the news
那是不是搶在新聞前
just make a splash or something
就先來個爆點或幹嘛
We feel that this kind of thing is ethical in this research
那這種事情我們覺得這個研究的倫理上
we are to follow
我們是要遵循的
It means following all the rules like this
就是說要遵循所有的規定這樣子
Why do we need state-run operations? Because there are actually very few regulations on state-run operations
這是為什麼我們要國營呢?因為國營其實規定很少
How do we kill and harvest
我們要怎麼殺怎麼採
But being a mouse requires a lot of rules
但是做到老鼠就規定很多了
Then when it comes to people, I think this is almost what it should be
然後到人的話這種我覺得這個是幾乎是應該是
I don't think it's advisable
不可取我覺得不可取
thank you professor
謝謝教授
hello that professor i think
那個教授你好我想
that's me to that one just now
就是我對那個剛剛那個
It’s just that the devouring part is a bit brutal
就是吞噬的部分就是有點蠻
I'm very interested, and I want to ask if there is one just now
蠻有興趣的然後想問一下剛剛不是有一張
Is that the Flash movie?
就是閃電的那個電影嗎?
Then I want to ask him that
那麼我想問一下他那個
The mechanism of lightning is because
閃電的那個機制是因為
Did Membre Procuretio change so that caused him to flash like this?
Membre Procuretio改變所以造成他這樣突然閃了一下嗎?
The first one is to use Eocasium's reporter
第一個是用Eocasium的reporter
I think you probably learned this
我想你大概是學這方面的
Then they feel that Membrane has a potential change
然後他們覺得Membrane有potential的改變
So all of a sudden it's a little easier to activate
所以突然之間它的activation就變得比較簡單一點
Suddenly
突然就一陣
In fact, it is more understandable why it looks like a lightning bolt.
那其實比較能理解的為什麼看起來像閃電這樣整根
just light up instead of saying this everywhere
就亮起來而不是說到處這樣子
do you know what i mean
你懂我意思嗎
why this one
就為什麼是這一根
then down again
然後再次下來
There is no certain order of which one comes first and which one comes after.
它到底哪一根先哪一根後是沒有一定的順序
I know that in terms of a single one it is that one suddenly is
我知道單就一根來講它是那一根突然就是
Because things outside the mold flow into that electric grid
因為模外的東西流到那個電柵裡面
so changing their potential
所以就改變了它們的電位
learn
了解
Thanks
謝謝
ok i have two questions
好 我有兩個問題
First, some people often dream
第一 有的人常常做夢
Make that teacher dream the same dream
讓那個老師夢相同的夢
He will eventually become his memory
他最後也會變成他的memory
That is to say, he will also be like that
就是說他也會好像那個
As you said, some Synapse forms
就像你講的有些那個 Synapse就形成
second question
第二個問題
that's what i think
就是我覺得
It seems that Alzheimer's is almost as much as this Parkinson's
好像阿茲海默的跟這個帕金森幾乎一樣多
So I'm very interested in the Pegasus effect you found
所以我對於這個你發現的天馬這個效果非常有興趣
Can it prevent PD? Or is it only effective through the BBB?
它是能預防PD嗎?還是也是要透過BBB才有效呢?
this is a good question
這個是好問題
This is a good question
這個都好有水準的問題
Will dreaming change the new nefs?
做夢會不會改變新nefs?
I...
我...
should be
才應該會喔
Don't talk about dreaming
其實不要說做夢啊
In fact, someone went to see the inside of these new nefs...
其實有人去看這些新nefs裡面的...
ah sorry
啊對不起
Highlight the expression of the protein inside
突出裡面的蛋白質的表達
In fact, day and night are very different
其實白天跟晚上就非常不一樣
The outstanding structure, the outstanding composition looks like this
突出的結構啦 突出的成分這樣子
then i want to dream
那我想做夢
sometimes you do remember
有時候你的確是會記得
then you can also take it as an experience
那你也可以把它當作一種經驗
it may make some changes to some prominence
它可能對某些突出會形成一些改變
i think it should be
我覺得應該這樣
that looks like my daughter probably
那像我女兒大概
she dreamed she remembered
她做了夢她都記得
She got up and told me what she did
她起來就跟我說她做了什麼
I probably don't even remember what dreams I had.
那我自己做什麼夢我大概都不記得
I don't know where the difference is
我不知道這個差異在哪裡
Well, I probably haven't done enough research on dreams.
那不過我大概對夢的研究也不夠多喔
The second question is that PD and ADO
第二個問題是說 PD跟ADO
In fact, Tianma is quite expensive.
其實天馬蠻貴的
This stinky coincidence actually I think
這個臭巧其實我覺得
Maybe we can change our lives and try today.
搞不好我們今天換個人生下去試
Maybe it will work
搞不好會有效果
take a what turmeric tree
拿一個什麼薑黃樹
you can listen to a lot
大家可以聽很多
These are some of the protective effects on the human body
這些都是對人體有保護作用的一些
Food or Chinese medicine like this
食材或者中藥這樣子
So I think from the point of view of protection and maintenance
所以我覺得就保護保養的觀點來講
In fact, there are no shortcomings, that's all I can say
其實沒什麼缺點我只能這樣講
But if you think this can be treated
但是如果你覺得這個可以治療
or what when i think
或幹嘛的時候我覺得
Actually, I have an experiment I want to tell you about
其實我有一個實驗我要跟大家講
You might actually feel a little disappointed
其實會讓你可能會覺得有點失望
Our fruit battalions are actually
我們這些果營事實上是
We started feeding Pegasus to it as soon as it was born
一出生以後我們就開始給它餵天馬
So let it grow strong and healthy from an early age
所以從小就讓它生強體魄體狀
So let's try to say let it start
那我們試著說讓它開始
When he is afraid of spiritual administration, let him feed the gods
出現怕精神施政的時候再給他餵天嘛
that's not invalid
那並不是沒有效
Probably for a week
大概是有一個禮拜的效果
that effect
那這個效果
Then a week later he started falling again
然後一個禮拜以後他又開始掉下去
Started to look sick again
又開始恢復生病的樣子
So the effect is not like
那所以這個效果沒有像
The effect of us being born and starting to feed
我們這個生下來開始餵的效果
that's why this gesture
那所以這個示好
It can also be said that there are some effects
也可以說有一些效果
Then if you live in camp for 60 days
那如果果營活60天的話
we figured it out
我們算過說
This week might be equal to seven human years.
這一個禮拜搞不好等於人的七年了
If the seven-year increase
那如果七年的增加的這個
good exercise health
好的運動的健康情況
It's actually not bad
其實也是不賴的
It's just whether our thing can
那只是我們這個東西能不能
transform it into a human
把它轉換成在人的身上
This is still to be studied
這個還是有待研究
Then we just want to say that it's okay for people
那我們只是希望說這可以對人的
Hello
你好
thank you professor for your speech
謝謝教授的演講
because there are two important messages
因為有兩則重要的訊息
I want to ask
我要請教一下
The first important message is to say
第一則重要的訊息就是說
The evolutionary degeneration of this brain activation
這個腦部的活化進化退化
it has a protein pattern
它有一種蛋白質圖樣
No, that electropowder
不,那個電粉質
Electropowder pattern protein
那個電粉質圖樣蛋白質
it can control
它能掌控的
is it true
這是不是事實
the second
第二個
This one is called expansion fish
一個叫擴魚的這個
This dimensional creature
這個維生物啊
it can transfer this memory
它可以把這個記憶轉移
Can these two phenomena
這兩種現象是不是能夠
please explain
請教導說明一下
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, I don't quite understand the second question
對,第二個問題我聽不太懂
Expansion fish
擴魚
A kind of vitamin
一種維生物啦
Seems
好像是
Its head looks like a snail
它那個頭好像跟蝸牛一樣
but it doesn't have that shell
但是它沒有那個殼
it is a mollusc
它是一個軟體動物
Broadfish
海闊魚
Applecia
Applecia
what is the problem with applecia
那Applecia的問題是什麼
that first question
那個第一問題
Ebeta cumulative this is
Ebeta累積這個是
Inside Alzheimer's
阿茲海默症裡面
one of the most common phenomena
最常見的一個現象
There's a lot of politics here
那這裡政論很多
some say it's harmful
有些說是有害的
that some say yes
那有些說是
In fact, it is protective
其實它是保護作用
Why because it means your nerve cells start
為什麼 因為就是說你神經細胞開始
produces an accumulation of protein and then it
產生蛋白質的累積 然後它就
it actually pushes it outside where it accumulates
它事實上把它排出去外面 在外面累積
That's a protective effect on nerve cells
那對神經細胞來講是一個保護作用
then many people
然後很多人
When they did that autopsy, they passed away.
他們做那個解剖的時候 就過世了解剖
Although they have Alzheimer's disease
雖然他們有發生阿茲海默症
It can be found that there are actually
可以發現說大腦裡面其實是有
The accumulation of this endoamylose, this Aβ
這個內澱粉這個Aβ的累積
What is this thing with
那這個東西到底跟
Alzheimer's disease is now believed by many people
阿茲海默症 現在很多人是相信有啦
But is it completely related?
不過是不是完全是有關聯性
Everyone has a little bit of this problem
大家也是有一點點這個問題
Then this has a great impact on the development of drugs
那這個對藥物的發展有一個很大的影響
Because many people take this amyloid Aβ thing
因為很多人就拿這個類澱粉 Aβ的東西
to be a target
來當作一個標的
Then he said that looking for medicine can prevent its aggregation like this
然後說找藥可以預防它的這個聚集這樣子
Then it will, you just asked that it will not spread, right?
那它會 你剛剛問題說會不擴散是不是
It can control its evolutionary degradation
它可以掌控它的這個進化退化
It needs this to control if it evolves
進化的話它需要這個來控制
Maybe it's a matter of the quantity.
可能是用那個份量的問題啦
it can add k and subtract
它可以加K減
can increase its
可以增加它的
to increase or decrease to increase
對 增加或是減少來增加
it reduces its function
它減少它的功能
to control its function
來掌控它的功能
function
功能啊
It says it can solve this geriatric syndrome
它說可以解決這個老人之待症
then i don't know it's true
那我不知道這是事實
Alzheimer's to the present
阿茲海摩症到現在
Seriously it's not the same
說真的還沒有一樣
Check this out online
上網路去查這個東西
There is indeed this thing
的確有這個東西在
That is to say, if the information
那也就是說這個信息的話
is possible
是有可能性
no medicine yet sorry
還沒有藥 對不起
as far as i know
就我所知啦
There is no effective medicine
還沒有好無效的藥
This answer does not answer no problem
這個回答不回答沒有問題
We just say there is this message
我們只是說有這個訊息存在
We know this thing
我們這個知道有這個東西
someone is working on this
有人在研究這個東西
That is to say, the future
也就是說這個未來
Our old man's disease can be solved
我們這個老人之待症能夠解決
Alzheimer's disease is this
阿茲海摩症是這個
This symptom can be resolved
這個症狀能夠解決
our health insurance
我們的健保啊
It now has 2.8 million of this age
它現在有280萬的這個高齡
Human life has been extending since it was opened
它開放以後人類的生命一直在延長
but this
可是這個
this human life
這個人類的生命
What happened to him after the scene
現場以後他所發生的一項
That is to say, the old man has his own administration and the bearer
也就是說老人自帶政和這個持物人
Will this rate of increase also increase?
這個增加率也會增加嘛
Is it that there will be social problems?
是不是 那就會遇到社會問題
Let's solve this problem from this aspect
我們就從這個方面來解決這個東西
Thanks
謝謝
people will be interesting
人都會有意思
Finally there will be a disease
最後會有一個病
The current parlance is to talk about healthy aging
現在的講法是說要健康的老化
the one you had before you died
就是在死之前你那個
It is not healthy for Taiwan to average 9 to 10 years now
台灣現在平均場9年到10年是不健康的
there is a problem here
這邊有一個問題
can i talk
我能不能講一下
Because Yang Zhiliang, Director of Health Yang Zhiliang said
因為楊智良 衛生署長楊智良他講
His goal
他的這個目標啊
He is old and never ends
他是老無極而終 老有所終
But this old and final
可是這個老和終啊
He is in a hurry, everything is a disease
他急啊 通通是一種病
He said that this cancer from 100%
他講這個癌症從100%
Up to now it is 100% and has been reduced to 30%
到現在是100% 一直減少到30%
Of course after 37% is resolved
當然在37%解決以後
The focus of his medical
他的這個醫療的重點
where is he going to put it
他要放在什麼地方呢
I think it might be above Laojihezhong
我想可能就在老急和中上面
Then the progress of our brain
那麼我們這個大腦的進步
If he can solve human problems
他能夠解決人類的問題的話
then everyone is like a young man
那每個人都像年輕人一樣
Can be lively and dare to run and jump
可以活活潑潑的最敢跑跳動
that's a very good thing
那是非常好的事情
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, are there any other questions on site?
好 現場還有沒有其他的問題
Hello teacher, I have a question
老師你好 請問有一個狀況
It's the old man who eats diarrhoea.
就是老人吃呆阿斯海膜症
Parkinson's disease is irreversible
帕金森市症這個都不可逆的
using drugs
使用藥物的話
It's just a delay
它是延緩作用而已嘛
is that so
是這樣嘛
That is to say, to delay the aggravation of the disease
就是說延緩病症加重
Is it getting heavier all the time?
一直加重嘛
Is that how it works?
是這樣的作用嘛
Yes, roughly speaking, it may be true.
是大致上講起來可能沒錯
But now I am most afraid of fitness disease
可是現在怕健身症症最
The latest treatment they're experimenting with is a modality
最新他們在試驗的一個治療的方式
what japan is doing is to say
日本在弄的就是說
Hit stem cells to
把幹細胞打到
stem cell
幹細胞
stem cell aging
幹細胞老化
stem cells into the brain
幹細胞打到大腦裡面去
dopamine zone
多巴胺的區域
Then this can replenish new nerve cells
那這可以補充新的神經細胞
So this is no longer
所以這個已經不是在
You can imagine that could be replaced by
你可以想像說可能是取代
It's not just slowing down those nerve cells.
不是在單純的延緩那些神經細胞的
That is to say, fear of mental loss can be dealt with in this way.
就是說怕精神失證可以這樣處理
in test
在試驗中
they are testing
他們在試驗中
They are doing human experiments
他們在做人體的試驗
Then I always thought he was completely irreversible
那我一直認為他是完全不可逆的
right
對啦
Thanks
謝謝
Is that a human experiment?
那是人體試驗嗎
yes
是
That's one of the Lobel speakers
那是那個洛貝爾來講得主的一個
their school
他們那學校那邊
he made that
他那個做出那個
IPS that
IPS那個
what's that chinese name
那個中文叫什麼
right
對
that stem cell therapy
那個幹細胞的治療
they lead that out of a
他們把那個引導出一個
this nerve cell
這種神經細胞
and then import it into the brain
然後再把它導入大腦裡面去
then they this
那他們這個
This is much different from what China said just now.
這個就跟剛剛中國講的差很多
they are strict
他們是有嚴格的
this test
這個試驗
RB pair
RB對
Then everything fits after
然後都一切都符合之後
Dare to do this test like this
才敢做這個試驗這樣子
Li Qingyun mentioned by the professor just now
剛才那個教授提到的李清雲
on the internet
網路上
means it's 256 years old
是說它有256歲
then under the same circumstances
那麼在相同的環境之下
can we find this
我們是不是可以找出這個
It can live to be 256 years old
它能夠活到256歲的這種
What about creating this same environment to increase human lifespan?
製造這種相同的環境來增加人類的壽命呢
Yes or no
是不是
There are indeed several places in the world
全世界的確有幾個地方
The average life expectancy of people is longer
人的平均壽命比較長
There is a longevity village in Japan, Italy or something
日本有一個長壽村 義大利 什麼的
So is it genetic or genetic?
那這個是基因的關係還是遺傳的關係
The relationship between the environment can actually be studied like this
環境的關係其實是可以去研究的這樣子
there is an average
那的確是有平均的
That is to say, you today, Li Qingyun, are alone
就是說你今天李清雲是一個人
one example
一個例子
For us to do experiments and do science
對我們做實驗做科學來講
N equals E is unreliable
N等於E是不可靠的
We all want N equal to several
我們都要N等於好幾個
We will say that this is preferable
我們才會說這個比較可取
Then part of Li Qingyun should be
那李清雲這個有一部分應該是
I don't know if it should be a rumor
不知道是不是應該是謠言
Because it's all word of mouth about this guy.
因為都靠口耳相傳說這個人
Some people say that my grandfather heard it when he was young
也有人說我爺爺小的時候聽過
Li Qingyun this person
李清雲這個人
so to speak
這樣就說
Retweet and say that this was in the pre-dragon period
回推 然後就說這個在前龍時期
Read it online, the story is very interesting and exciting
那個上網去看 那故事很有趣 很精彩
But then this this
可是 然後這個這個
Newspapers are reporting this
報紙都在報導這樣子
But that New York Times 100 years ago
可是那個那個100年前的New York Times
Who knows if there will be false reports?
是不是也會有錯誤的報導這個誰知道
So you can go and see
所以大家可以去看看
as entertainment news
當作一個娛樂新聞
I think it's good
我覺得是不錯
that's not to mislead people
那不是要誤導大家
Okay, is there anyone here with any questions?
好 現場還有沒有哪一位有問題
No, we have a network here
沒有啦 我們這裡有一個網路上面的
Ask Mr. Jane what I have learned so far
請教簡老師目前了解到
Molecular Mechanisms of Artmap Degradation
術圖退化的分子機制
Causality with electrophysiological properties
與電生理特性的因果性
is due to the degradation of the molecule
是因為分子造成退化
Does static ear cause the degradation of electrophysiological properties?
而靜耳造成電生理特性的退化嗎
Or the electrophysiological changes will be reversed
還是電生理的改變會反過來
cause genetic changes
造成基因的改變
Both directions are possible
兩個方向都有可能啦
That is to say, its electrophysiological properties are basically
就是說 它的電生理特性基本上就
Even the conduction in electrogenesis actually relies a lot on protein
就是電生裡的傳導其實也靠得很多是蛋白質
The Membrane protein channel on the cell surface
在細胞表面的那個Membrane protein channel
or something
或什麼的
Then there is a problem with these proteins, there is a problem with speed
那這些蛋白質有問題 速度有問題
then the protein decreases
然後蛋白質減少
That will of course cause changes in the electrophysiology
那當然會引起電生裡的變化
What's not normal in that electrician
那電生裡的不正常
For example, a conduction that is too strong, conduction of electricity
譬如說太強的一個傳導 電的傳導
That could also cause injury at the speed itself
那也可能會造成這個速度本身的受傷
Then I think both ways are possible
然後就 我覺得雙向都是有可能的
Okay, the second question is
好 第二個問題是
I would like to ask whether Parkinson's is the same as the general aging condition
想請問帕金森是跟一般老化的狀況
Is the molecular mechanism of his neurotic speed retreat different?
他的這個神經人速度退縮的分子機制是不是不一樣
i think it's different
我覺得是不一樣
This can be seen that this found the gene
這個可以看得到這個找到了基因
Parkinson's has genes like Parkinson's own
帕金森有帕金森自己這一類的基因
Alzheimer's this Alzheimer's this other kind of gene
阿茲海摩這種 阿茲海摩這種另外一類的基因
These genes are actually different
這些基因其實不太一樣
So it should be. I think the molecular mechanism may be different.
那所以說應該是 我覺得是分子機制可能是不一樣的這樣子
Well, is there any problem at the scene?
那 好 現場還有沒有問題
i want to ask a question
我要問一個問題
Suppose the results of this experiment shown here
假設這邊秀的這個實驗的結果
you give it gastrodia elata
你給它吃天麻
0.1% is very effective
0.1%很有效
Then 0.5% and 1% are not very effective
然後0.5%和1%就不太有效
So does this mean that eating too much won't help?
所以這是不是說吃太多也不會有用
right
對
that
那個
We've tried other bases and it's shown here
我們試過其他基量這裡面秀出來
Its 0.02% doesn't do much either
它0.02%也沒有什麼效果
So swallowing it is actually 0.1% which is the most effective.
那吞到其實是0.1%是最有效的這樣子
Then we know that the reaction to this drug is often a
那我們知道這個藥物的反應常常是一個
Are they called U-SHIPs?
它們叫做U-SHIP有沒有
and then just about to
然後剛剛好要
or a MERSH
或一個MERSH
MERSH by itself
MERSH自行
Just the right amount of base is the best
剛剛好的基量效果是最好
too little too much
太少太多都不行
So we often say that you should follow the doctor's instructions to take medicine
所以我們常常說你要遵從醫師的指示服藥
in this way
就這種道理
Because of its high concentration of course
因為它的當然濃度高的時候
It may act on other molecules
它可能會去作用到別的分子作用
If there is too little, it may not be enough.
那太少的話可能就不夠這樣子
So this is a
所以這個是一個
yes
對啊
So this result is actually grandson, you ask me
所以這個結果其實孫子你問我
Don't take it by yourself when you go home
回家不要自己隨便服用
too much can be problematic
太多可能會出現問題
Okay, the last one will ask you later
好 最後那位等一下再問你
Excuse me, professor, you just said
請問教授 剛剛您說
When you use Pegasus
你們使用天馬的時候
It is the use of scientifically concentrated traditional Chinese medicine
是使用科學濃縮中藥
extraction
萃取
yes
是
we all try
我們都有試喔
Concentrated
濃縮的有
then additionally
然後另外
This experiment proved that concentrated
這個實驗證明是濃縮的
We have put the principal components inside
我們有把裡面的主成分
called Gasodin
叫做Gasodin
tried
試過
that works too
那個也有效
But not as good as this
但是沒有這個效果好
so it looks like
所以看起來
It's actually several ingredients together
它事實上是要好幾個成分在一起
It might work best like this
效果可能會最好這樣子
ask one more
再問一個
Just happened to be right
就是剛好沒有看錯
just now your slime shows
剛剛你那個slime shows
There are more sketches about the autism
說那個自閉症的那個素圖比較多
Sutu
素圖
Then Lomo's normal down
然後Lomo的正常下來
Then the other one is called
然後其他的那個就所謂的
mental disorder
思覺失調
I'm just wondering if autistic people are less likely to get treatment from Bakis
我是好奇想會不會自閉這個人比較不容易得到巴基斯的治療
Relatively speaking
相對來講
this is a good question
這個是個好問題
I'm guessing
我是在這麼揣擦
I never thought about this
這個我沒想過
That fear is like this in this life
那個怕今生是這樣
For example, for some diseases, sometimes some investigations will find that this is indeed the case
譬如說有些疾病其實有時候有些調查會發現的確是這樣
Even before, there was a person who taught the most general way of speaking
甚至以前有一個人講法最很一般的講法
That means people with cancer don't get that
就是說得癌症的人不會得那個
Neural push
神經推話
You won't get cancer if you get nervous
得神經推話不會得癌症
Then they came up with a theory
那他們有提出一套理論
this one with protein
跟蛋白質的這個
folding is related
folding有關係
Protein folding is related to
蛋白質的折疊有關係
Even if this life has something to do with Alzheimer's disease
那怕今生跟阿茲海摩症其實有一些
Protect
保護
There are some things that are actually being investigated now
有一些東西其實是現在調查出來
Some factors have had an impact on him.
有些因素對他的影響其實是滿
full of effect
滿有效果
some effect
有些效果
The greatest effect on the two diseases
對這兩個疾病最大的影響效果
is age
是年紀
The best age to talk about now
現在最能夠講的年紀
The older you get, the higher your memory of getting sick
年紀越大得病的記憶越高
The second most effective thing is exercise
第二最有效的東西是運動
Most sports have a great effect on this
大部分運動對這個都有很大的效果
There are some reasons that I can't tell
那有一些不太能夠講的原因
For example, drinking coffee is actually right
譬如說喝咖啡其實說對
Mr Pan has some effect
潘先生先生有一些效果
But the effect is very small, so don't write it down
可是效果很少,所以不用記下來
Go back and drink more?
回去多喝沒有
can't sleep at night
晚上睡不著喔
Then there is another one that everyone is afraid to say
然後還有一個大家不太敢講的
is smoking
是抽菸
Once you talk about it, it will be troublesome
一講了就麻煩了
People who smoke say I have a reason to smoke
抽菸的人就說我有理由可以抽菸
Well, if you actually smoke, that's right.
那其實抽菸的話對
Alzheimer's and Mr. Pan have a little protective effect
阿茲海莫森跟潘先生先生有一點點保護效果
This is also your game to read literature
這也是去看文獻你們的遊戲
But everyone is afraid to speak, sorry to speak
可是大家都不太敢講,不好意思講
I'm talking secretly now, please don't say that
那我現在是偷偷講,請不要那個
please don't promote
請不要宣傳
But in fact there are reporters
不過這事實上是都有記者
Let me add that this type of research is all about correlation
我補充一下,這一類的研究都是關聯性
who you statistically smoke
就是你統計上抽菸的人
What are the odds of getting this?
和得這個的機率是怎麼樣
It's not about smoking
並不是說抽菸這個行為
will affect this matter
就會影響到這件事情
OK, are we still there?
好,我們現場還有沒有
friends have problems
朋友有問題的
please
請
That is, there are three nerves on the edge of the four nerves
就是那個四神經緣有三個
just mentioned three
剛剛提到三個
one is that shape
一個就是那個形狀
on the edge
就邊緣線
one is color
一個是顏色
Then another judgment is his dynamic
然後另外一個判斷是他的動態
that such a
那這樣的一個
Is it because his body's four nerves have different divisions of labor?
就是他的本體四神經緣有不同的分工嗎
Are there any that are more sensitive to color?
有沒有哪一些是針對顏色比較敏感
Is there any division of labor in these nerve borders?
就是這些神經緣有沒有做一些分工
Or is it that the entire nerve border of our tetraretina is
還是說整個我們的四網膜的神經緣都是
Same work and same hatred
同工 同仇
and then add different dimensions
然後去增設不同的向度
you asked a good question
你這問題問得很好
I'm not an expert there
那個我不是那邊專家
But I can give you some simple answers
不過可以給你一些簡單的回答
The first one is called parallel processing
第一個他們這個叫parallel processing
is processed together
就是一起處理的
They do divide labor
他們的確是分工
look at the color
那看顏色的看顏色
The color is also divided into red green blue
顏色還分紅色 綠色 藍色
three colors
三種顏色
red is only for humans
紅色只有人類才有
You go to some monkeys or to the general east house that red is gone
你到一些猴子或到一般東屋那個紅色就不見了
So we humans can see roses
所以我們人可以看得到玫瑰花的
beautiful roses
漂亮的玫瑰花
That
那
then that
然後那個
are different four nerves far in
是不同的四神經遠在
look at different things
看不同的東西
then put together
然後整合在一起
So our eyes are actually very powerful
所以我們的眼睛其實是非常厲害
Sorry to add a related
對不起 追加一個相關的
because i teach art
因為我是教藝術的
Then it seems that boys are less sensitive to social feelings
然後好像男生對社感比較不敏感
right
對
then to that
然後對那個
in shape
就形體
they have a good grasp
他們掌握得還不錯
is a boy
就是男生
you go to the department store
你去百貨公司
Boys, look what you all wear
男生的 你看你們都穿的
It's those colors
就是那幾個顏色啦
keep it simple
講簡單就這樣
Then they say women are more like children
那他們說女人比較像小孩
That color is very colorful
那顏色非常的Colorful
And there will be a very detailed analysis
而且會有做很細膩的分析
It's also a human
這也是一個人類的
A division of labor for the development of an entire culture
整個文化發展的一個分工
some are
有些就是
Demon offers nerves to destroy it
魔獻神經它打掉
just don't be too sensitive
就是不要太敏感
I can say this, it's not good for boys, it's not good for girls
這個我就可以講了,對男生不利,對女生不利
We have a gene that recognizes red, it seems to be X
我們有一條,認紅色的這個基因,好像是X
If you know X, there is only one for boys and two for girls
你如果知道X,男生只有一條,女生只有兩條的
This boy is prone to mutations, so boys have a lot of color
這個男生容易產生突變,所以男生很多色芒
Some people are more sensitive to color, in fact, the photoreceptor cells
有些人對顏色比較敏感,其實那個感光細胞
That is to say, apart from recognizing red, he may have a little difference in length
就是說他除了認紅色,他可能有一點點破長的差別
He may have different neurons to detect him
他可能可以有不同的神經細胞去把他偵測到
So some people are really sensitive to those who study art or clothes design like you
所以有些人對像你們學藝術的,或者衣服設計,他們真的是很敏感
like us , like me is very insensitive
像我們,像我的話就很不敏感
I probably only do experiments to see red, green and blue mixed together like this
我大概做實驗都只會看紅色、綠色跟藍色這樣混合在一起而已
Then there is indeed a natural difference
那這個的確是有天生上的差異
As I mentioned just now, there are also animals, some of which cannot see red
那我剛剛有提到,動物也有,有些是看不到紅色
ok , we are running out of time , our last question
好,我們時間差不多了,我們最後一個問題
I can add to the lady's question just now
我可以補充一下剛剛那位女士的問題
She didn't mean that we were...
她不是說就是我們是...
Our nerve cells have a division of labor on the image
我們的神經細胞是在影像上面有分工
My answer is to try
我答案是試的啦
Then its division of labor
然後它的分工機制的話
The color is that there is a kind of sight-seeking cells on our social membrane.
顏色的話就是我們社網膜上面有一種叫做視追細胞
It can identify RGB three colors
它可以辨認RGB三種顏色
There should be this related connection in fine arts
在美術學應該是有這個相關的連接的
So we can identify RGB
所以我們就是可以辨認RGB
Then use its brightness's
然後用它的亮度的
It is to disassemble it to show our various colors
就是拆去呈現出我們各種不同的顏色
Then in terms of pure brightness
然後在純粹以亮度來表現的話
There is another type called sight-seeking cells
又有另外一種叫做視追細胞
it can be compared for brightness
它可以針對明亮程度做比較
And finally the part of that shape
然後最後是那個形狀的部分的話
Mainly when some visual areas of the brain are doing calculations
主要是在大腦的一些視覺區在運算的時候
it will have specific different cells
它會有特定的不同的細胞
is to analyze its shape or the direction it moves
就是分析它的形狀或它移動的方向
then activates a specific population of cells in the visual area
然後會活化視覺區的特定的一群細胞
Do more advanced processing
做更高級的處理
Thanks
謝謝
ok thank you very well said
好 謝謝講得很好
ok then i think our time is up
好 那我想我們時間到了
Thank you for your enthusiastic participation today
謝謝今天大家這個熱情踴躍的參與
Hope we can come again in December
期望我們12月份大家還能夠再來
Thanks
謝謝